They call you the godfather of AI. So
他们称你为人工智能之父。 那么，
their career prospects in a world of
在一个超级智能的世界里，你会如何向人们描述他们的职业前景呢
super intelligence? Train to be a
？ 接受培训成为一名
plumber. Really? Yeah. Okay. I'm going
水管工。 真的吗？ 是的。 好的。 我要去当
to become a plumber. Jeffrey Hinton is
一名水管工。 杰弗里·辛顿是
the Nobel Prize winning pioneer whose
诺贝尔奖得主，这位先驱者以其
groundbreaking work has shaped AI and
开创性的工作塑造了人工智能和
the future of humanity. Why do they call
人类的未来。 为什么人们称它为
it the godfather of AI? because there
人工智能之父？ 因为当时
weren't many people who believed that we
很少有人相信我们
could model AI on the brain so that it
可以用大脑来模拟人工智能，使其
learned to do complicated things like
学会做一些复杂的事情，比如
recognize objects and images or even do
识别物体和图像，甚至进行
reasoning. And I pushed that approach
推理。 我推广这种方法长达
for 50 years and then Google acquired
50 年，后来谷歌收购了
that technology and I worked there for
这项技术，我在那里工作了
10 years on something that's now used
10 年，从事的技术现在
all the time in AI. And then you left.
在人工智能领域被广泛应用。 然后你就离开了。   是的
Yeah. Why? So that I could talk freely
。 为什么？ 这样我就可以
at a conference. What did you want to
在会议上畅所欲言了。 你想
talk about freely? How dangerous AI
畅所欲言地聊些什么？ 人工智能可能有多危险？
I realized that these things will one
我意识到，这些东西总有一天会
day get smarter than us. And we've never
比我们更聪明。 我们从未遇到过这种情况
had to deal with that. And if you want
。 如果你想
to know what life's like when you're not
知道当你不是
the apex intelligence, ask a chicken. So
最高智慧生物时，生活会是什么样子，那就去问问鸡吧。 因此，
there's risks that come from people
人们
misusing AI. And then there's risks from
滥用人工智能会带来风险。 此外，
AI getting super smart and deciding it
人工智能变得过于智能并认为它
doesn't need us. Is that a real risk?
不再需要我们，这会带来风险。 那真的存在风险吗？   是的
Yes, it is. But they're not going to
。 但他们不会
stop it cuz it's too good for too many
阻止它，因为它用途太广了
things. What about regulations? They
。 那么监管方面呢？ 他们
have some, but they're not designed to
有一些应对威胁的手段，但这些手段并不能
deal with most of the threats. Like the
应对大多数威胁。 例如，
European regulations have a clause that
欧洲法规中有一项条款规定，
say none of these apply to military uses
这些规定均不适用于人工智能的军事用途
of AI. Really? Yeah. It's crazy. One of
。 真的吗？ 是的。 太疯狂了。
your students left OpenAI. Yeah. He was
你们的一名学生离开了 OpenAI。 是的。 他可能是
versions of church GPT and I think he
教会早期 GPT 版本开发过程中最重要的人物，我认为他
left because he had safety concerns. We
离开是因为出于安全考虑。 我们
should recognize that this stuff is an
应该认识到，这关乎人类的生存
existential threat and we have to face
，我们必须面对这样的
the possibility that unless we do
可能性：如果我们不
something soon we're near the end. So
尽快采取行动，世界末日就将来临。 所以，
let's do the risks. What do we end up
让我们承担这些风险吧。
doing in such a world?
在这样的世界里，我们最终会做什么？
This has always blown my mind a little
这件事一直让我有点难以置信
bit. 53% of you that listen to the show
。 经常收听该节目的听众中，有 53% 的人
regularly haven't yet subscribed to the
尚未订阅该
show. So, could I ask you for a favor
节目。 那么，在我们开始之前，我能请你帮个忙吗
before we start? If you like the show
？ 如果你喜欢我们的节目，
and you like what we do here and you
喜欢我们在这里所做的一切，并且
want to support us, the free simple way
想要支持我们，最简单的免费方法
that you can do just that is by hitting
就是点击
the subscribe button. And my commitment
订阅按钮。 我向
to you is if you do that, then I'll do
你们承诺，如果你们这样做，
everything in my power, me and my team,
我和我的团队将竭尽全力，
to make sure that this show is better
确保这个节目
for you every single week. We'll listen
每周都能为你们带来更好的体验。 我们会认真听取
to your feedback. We'll find the guests
您的反馈意见。 我们会找到您
that you want me to speak to and we'll
希望我采访的嘉宾，并
continue to do what we do. Thank you so
继续做好我们一直在做的事情。 太感谢了
much.
。
Jeffrey Hinsson, they call you the
杰弗里·欣森，人们称你为
godfather of AI.
人工智能之父。   是的，
Uh yes they do. Why do they call you
他们确实有。 他们为什么那样称呼你
that? There weren't that many people who
？ 当时
believed that we could make neural
相信我们能够让神经
networks work, artificial neural
网络，也就是人工神经
networks. So for a long time in AI from
网络发挥作用的人并不多。 因此，从
the 1950s onwards, there were kind of
20 世纪 50 年代开始，人工智能领域长期以来存在着两种关于
two ideas about how to do AI.
如何进行人工智能的想法。
One idea was that sort of core of human
其中一种观点认为，人类
intelligence was reasoning. And to do
智能的核心是推理能力。 而要进行
reasoning, you needed to use some form
推理，就需要运用某种
of logic. And so AI had to be based
逻辑。 因此，人工智能必须以
around logic. And in your head, you must
逻辑为基础。 在你的脑海里，一定
have something like symbolic expressions
存在类似符号表达式的东西，
that you manipulated with rules. And
你可以用规则来操控它们。
that's how intelligence worked. And
这就是情报运作的方式。 而
things like learning or reasoning by
像学习或类比推理之类的能力
analogy, that all come later once we've
，都是在我们
figured out how basic reasoning works.
弄清楚基本推理是如何运作之后才会出现的。
There was a different approach, which is
还有一种不同的方法，那就是
to say, let's model AI on the brain
，让我们以大脑为模型来构建人工智能，
because obviously the brain makes us
因为很显然，大脑使我们变得
intelligent. So simulate a network of
聪明。 因此，
brain cells on a computer and try and
在计算机上模拟一个脑细胞网络，并尝试
figure out how you would learn strengths
弄清楚如何学习
of connections between brain cells so
脑细胞之间连接的强度，
that it learned to do complicated things
以便它能够学习做一些复杂的事情，
like recognize objects in images or
例如识别图像中的物体、
recognize speech or even do reasoning. I
识别语音，甚至进行推理。 我
pushed that approach for like 50 years
坚持这种方法长达50年，
because so few people believed in it.
因为很少有人相信它。   当时
There weren't many good universities
很少有优秀的大学设有
that had groups that did that. So if you
这样的社团。 所以，如果你这样做，那些
believed in that came and worked with
认同这种理念的最优秀的年轻学生就会来和
you. So I was very fortunate in getting
你一起工作。 因此，我很幸运地招收了
a whole lot of really good students some
很多非常优秀的学生，其中一些人
of which have gone on to create and play
后来创建了像 OpenAI 这样的平台，并
an instrumental role in creating
在创建过程中发挥了重要作用
platforms like open AI. Yes. So I sus
。 是的。 所以，我举了
a nice example a whole bunch of them.
一个很好的例子，很多都是这样。
Why did you believe that modeling it off
你为什么认为以
the brain was a more effective approach?
大脑为原型进行建模是一种更有效的方法？
It wasn't just me believed it early on.
不仅仅是我，很多人很早就相信这一点。
Fonoyman believed it and Cheuring
福诺伊曼相信这一点，切林也
believed it and if either of those had
相信这一点，如果他们中的任何一个
lived I think AI would have had a very
活下来，我认为人工智能的
different history but they both died
历史将会截然不同，但他们都
young. You think AI would have been here
英年早逝。 你认为人工智能本应
sooner? I think neural net the neural
更早出现吗？ 我认为，
much sooner if either of them had lived
如果他们俩生活
in this season of your life. What
在你这个时代，神经网络方法早就被接受了。
mission are you on? My main mission now
你正在执行什么任务？ 我现在的主要任务
is to warn people how dangerous AI could
是警告人们人工智能可能带来的危险
be. Did you know that when you became
。 你知道吗？你就是
the godfather of AI? No, not really. I
人工智能之父。 不，其实不是。 我反应
was quite slow to understand some of the
比较慢，没能完全理解其中的一些
risks. Some of the risks were always
风险。 有些风险一直
very obvious, like people would use AI
都很明显，比如人们会利用人工智能
to make autonomous lethal weapons. That
制造自主致命武器。 那
is things that go around deciding by
是一些会
themselves who to kill. Other risks,
自行决定杀谁的东西。 其他风险，
like the idea that they would one day
比如他们有一天
get smarter than us and maybe would
会变得比我们更聪明，甚至可能
become irrelevant, I was slow to
变得无关紧要，我当时并没有
recognize that. Other people recognized
意识到。 其他人早在
it 20 years ago. I only recognized it a
20年前就认识到了这一点。 直到几年前我才意识到，
few years ago that that was a real risk
那是一个真实存在的风险，而且
that was come might be coming quite
可能
soon. How could you not have foreseen
很快就会到来。 以你对
about cracking the ability for these
破解
computers to learn similar to how humans
计算机学习能力（类似于人类
learn and just you know introducing any
学习的方式）以及引入任何
rate of improvement? It's a very good
改进速度的了解，你怎么可能没有预见到这一点呢？ 这是一个很好的
question. How could you not have seen
问题。 你怎么可能没看到
that? But remember neural networks 20 30
？ 但请记住，20 30 年前的神经网络
years ago were very primitive in what
在功能上还非常原始
they could do. They were nowhere near as
。 虽然他们远
good as humans, but things like vision
不如人类，但在视觉
and language and speech recognition. The
、语言和语音识别等方面却很出色。
idea that you have to now worry about it
现在居然有人担心它
getting smarter than people, that seems
会变得比人类更聪明，这听起来很
silly then. When did that change? It
荒谬。 这种情况是什么时候改变的？
chat GPT came out. It changed for me
聊天 GPT 的出现改变了普通大众的聊天方式。
when I realized that the kinds of
当我意识到
digital intelligences we're making have
我们正在创造的数字智能具有某种
something that makes them far superior
特性，使其远胜于
we have. If I want to share information
我们拥有的生物智能时，我的想法发生了改变。 如果我想
with you, so I go off and I learn
和你分享信息，所以我去学习
something and I'd like to tell you what
一些东西，然后我想告诉你
I learned. So I produce some sentences.
我学到了什么。 于是我造了一些句子。
This is a rather simplistic model, but
这是一个相当简单的模型，但
roughly right. Your brain is trying to
大致正确。 你的大脑正在试图
figure out how can I change the strength
弄清楚如何改变
of connections between neurons. So I
神经元之间的连接强度。 所以我
might have put that word next. And so
可能把那个词放在了后面。 所以，
you'll do a lot of learning when a very
当遇到一个非常出乎意料的词时，你会学到很多东西；而当遇到一个
learning when if it's when it's very
非常
obvious word. If I say fish and chips,
显而易见的词时，你则学不到太多东西。 如果我说炸鱼薯条，而
you don't do much learning when I say
我说薯条，那你学到的东西就不多了
chips. But if I say fish and cucumber,
。 但如果我说鱼和黄瓜，
you do a lot more learning. You wonder
你就能学到更多东西。 你想知道
why did I say cucumber? So that's
我为什么说黄瓜吗？ 这就是
roughly what's going on in your brain.
你大脑中大致发生的情况。
I'm predicting what's coming next.
我预测接下来会发生什么。
That's how we think it's working. Nobody
我们认为它就是这样运作的。 没有人
really knows for sure how the brain
真正确切地知道大脑是如何
works. And nobody knows how it gets the
运作的。 没有人知道它是如何获得
information about whether you should
关于应该
increase the strength of a connection or
增强连接强度还是
decrease the strength of a connection.
减弱连接强度的信息的。
That's the crucial thing. But what we do
这是关键所在。 但我们
know now from AI
现在从人工智能中了解到，
is that if you could get information
如果你能够获得
about whether to increase or decrease
关于是应该增加还是减少
the connection strength so as to do
连接强度的信息，以便在
better at whatever task you're trying to
你尝试完成的任何任务中做得更好
do, then we could learn incredible
，那么我们就能学到不可思议的
things because that's what we're doing
事情，因为这就是我们
now with artificial neuronets.
现在用人工神经网络所做的事情。   只是
It's just we don't know for real brains
我们不知道真正的大脑是
how they get that signal about whether
如何获得
to increase or decrease.
增加或减少的信号的。
As we sit here today, what are the big
今天，
concerns you have around safety of AI?
您认为人工智能安全方面最大的担忧是什么？
if we were to to list the the top couple
如果要列出我们最先
that are really front of mind and that
想到、最
we should be thinking about. Um, can I
应该考虑的几对情侣。 嗯，我可以
have more than a couple? Go ahead. I'll
要不止一对吗？ 前进。 我会把
write them all down and we'll go through
它们都写下来，然后我们逐一查看
them. Okay. First of all, I want to make
。 好的。 首先，我想
a distinction between two completely
区分两种完全
different kinds of risk.
不同的风险。
There's risks that come from people
人们
misusing AI. Yeah. And that's most of
滥用人工智能会带来风险。 是的。 这就是大部分
the risks and all of the short-term
风险和所有短期
risks. And then there's risks that come
风险。 此外，
from AI getting super smart and deciding
人工智能变得非常智能，并认为
it doesn't need us. Is that a real risk?
它不再需要我们，这也会带来风险。 那真的存在风险吗？
And I talk mainly about that second risk
我主要谈论的是第二个风险，
because lots of people say, "Is that a
因为很多人会问：“这是一个
real risk?" And yes, it is. Now, we
真正的风险吗？” 是的，的确如此。 现在，我们
don't know how much of a risk it is.
还不知道这究竟有多大风险。
We've never been in that situation
我们以前从未遇到过这种情况
before. We've never had to deal with
。 我们从未遇到过比
things smarter than us. So really, the
我们更聪明的事物。 所以说，
thing about that existential threat is
这种生存威胁的关键在于
that we have no idea how to deal with
我们根本不知道该如何应对
it. We have no idea what it's going to
。 我们完全不知道它会是什么样子
look like. And anybody who tells you
。 任何告诉你
they know just what's going to happen
他们知道将会发生什么
and how to deal with it, they're talking
以及如何应对的人，都是在
nonsense. So, we don't know how to
胡说八道。 所以，我们不知道如何
estimate the probabil probabilities
估计
it'll replace us. Um, some people say
它取代我们的概率。 嗯，有人说
it's like less than 1%. My friend Yan
这个比例不到1%。 我的朋友 Yan
Lar who was a postto with me thinks no
Lar 和我一起在 Postto 工作，他认为
no no, we're always going to be we build
不不不，我们总是会建造
these things. We're always going to be
这些东西。 我们始终会
in control. We'll build them to be
掌控局面。 我们将把它们培养成服从
obedient.
命令的人。
And other people like Yudkowski say,
还有像尤德科夫斯基这样的人说：
"No, no, no. These things are going to
“不，不，不。这些东西
wipe us out for sure. If anybody builds
肯定会把我们毁灭。如果有人建造了
it, it's going to wipe us all out." And
它，它就会把我们全部毁灭。”
he's confident of that. I think both of
他对此充满信心。 我认为这两种
those positions are extreme. It's very
观点都过于极端。
hard to estimate the probabilities in
很难估计中间的概率
between. If you had to bet on who was
。 如果让你
right out of your two friends,
在两个朋友中选一个猜对的，
I simply don't know. So, if I had to
我真的不知道。 所以，如果非要我
bet, I'd say the probabilities in
下注的话，我会说概率介于
between, and I don't know where to
两者之间，但我不知道该如何
estimate it in between. I often say 10
估计这个中间值。 我经常说他们有 10%
to 20% chance they'll wipe us out, but
到 20% 的几率会消灭我们，但这
that's just gut based on the idea that
只是基于
we're we're still making them and we're
我们仍在制造他们，而且我们
pretty ingenious. And the hope is that
相当聪明的想法的直觉。 我们希望，
if enough smart people do enough
如果足够多的聪明人投入
research with enough resources, we'll
足够的资源进行足够的研究，就能
figure out a way to build them so
找到一种方法来制造出
they'll never want to harm us. Sometimes
永远不会伤害我们的生物。 有时
I think if we we talk about that second
我会想，如果我们谈论第二条
um path, sometimes I think about nuclear
道路，有时我会想到
bombs and the the invention of the
核弹和
atomic bomb and how it compares like how
原子弹的发明，以及它们之间的比较，比如
is this different because the atomic
这有什么不同，因为
bomb came along and I imagine a lot of
原子弹出现后，我想
people at that time thought our days are
当时很多人都认为我们的日子
numbered. Yes, I was there. We did.
屈指可数了。 是的，我当时也在场。 我们做到了。   是的
Yeah. But but but what's what h we're
。 但是，但是，但是，我们为什么
still here. We're still here. Yes. So
还在这里？ 我们依然在这里。 是的。 所以
the atomic bomb was really only good for
原子弹实际上只有
one thing and it was very obvious how it
一个用途，而且它的工作原理也很明显
worked. Even if you hadn't had the
。 即使你没有看过
pictures of Hiroshima and Nagasaki, it
广岛和长崎的照片，也很
was obvious that it was a very big bomb
明显，那是一颗威力巨大、
that was very dangerous. With AI,
非常危险的原子弹。 人工智能有
it's good for many, many things. It's
很多用途。 人工智能
going to be magnificent in healthcare
将在医疗保健
and education and more or less any
和教育领域发挥巨大作用，而且几乎所有
industry that needs to use its data is
需要使用数据的行业都将能够借助
AI. So, we're not going to stop the
人工智能更好地利用数据。 所以，我们不会停止
development.
研发。
You know, people say, "Well, why don't
你知道，人们会说，“那我们为什么不
we just stop it now?" We're not going to
现在就阻止它呢？” 我们不会
stop it because it's too good for too
停止它，因为它用途太广了
many things. Also, we're not going to
。 此外，我们不会
stop it because it's good for battle
阻止它，因为它对战斗
robots, and none of the countries that
机器人有好处，而且没有哪个
sell weapons are going to want to stop
武器销售国会想阻止
it. Like the European regulations, they
它。 与欧洲的法规一样，他们也
have some regulations about AI, and it's
对人工智能有一些规定，制定
good they have some regulations, but
一些规定是好事，但这些规定并
they're not designed to deal with most
不能应对
of the threats. And in particular, the
大多数威胁。 尤其值得注意的是，
European regulations have a a clause in
欧洲法规中有一条条款规定，
them that say none of these regulations
这些法规均不
apply to military uses of AI.
适用于人工智能的军事用途。
So governments are willing to regulate
所以政府愿意
regulate companies and people, but
监管公司和个人，但却
they're not willing to regulate
不愿意监管
themselves.
自己。
It seems pretty crazy to me that they I
我觉得这很疯狂，他们
go back and forward, but if Europe has a
来回摇摆不定，但如果欧洲有相关
regulation, but the rest of the world
规定，而世界其他地方
doesn't
没有，就会造成
competitive disadvantage. Yeah, we're
竞争劣势。 是的，我们已经
seeing this already. I don't think
看到这种情况了。 我认为
people realize that when OpenAI release
人们没有意识到，当 OpenAI 在美国发布
a new model or a new piece of software
新模型或新软件时
in America, they can't release it to
，
Europe yet because of regulations here.
由于这里的法规限制，他们还不能在欧洲发布。
So Sam Alman tweeted saying, "Our new AI
因此，Sam Alman 在推特上发文称：“我们新的 AI
agent thing is available to everybody,
代理功能对所有人开放，
but it can't come to Europe yet because
但由于监管规定，它目前还无法进入欧洲市场
there's regulations."
。”   是的
Yes. What does that gives us a
。 这给我们带来了哪些
productive disadvantage? Productivity
生产上的劣势？ 生产力
disadvantage. What we need is I mean at
劣势。 我的意思是，在当今这个
this point in history when we're about
历史节点，当我们即将
to produce things more intelligent than
创造出比我们自身更智能的事物时
ourselves, what we really need is a kind
，我们真正需要的是一种
of world government that works run by
由
intelligent, thoughtful people. And
有智慧、有思想的人管理的、运转良好的世界政府。 但
that's not what we got.
我们得到的却不是那样。
So free-for-all. Well, that what we've
所以，一切随心所欲。 嗯，我们现在
got is sort of
拥有的，某种程度上来说，就是
we've got capitalism which is done very
我们把资本主义运作得非常
nicely by us. is produce lots of goods
出色。 它
goods and services for us. But these big
为我们生产大量的商品和服务。 但是这些大
companies, they're legally required to
公司在法律上有义务尽可能地
try and maximize profits and that's not
追求利润最大化，而这并不是
what you want from the people developing
你希望从开发
this stuff.
这些东西的人身上看到的。
So let's do the risks then. You talked
那么，我们就来承担这些风险吧。 你提到过
about there's human risks and then
人为风险，还有……
there's So I've distinguished these two
所以我区分了这两种
kinds of risk. Let's talk about all the
风险。 我们来谈谈
risks from bad human actors using AI.
恶意人员利用人工智能带来的所有风险。
There's cyber attacks.
网络攻击层出不穷。
So between 2023 and 2024,
因此，在 2023 年至 2024 年间，
they increased by about a factor of
它们增长了约
12,200%.
12200%。
And that's probably because these large
这可能是因为这些大型
language models make it much easier to
语言模型使得
do fishing attacks. And a fishing attack
进行钓鱼攻击变得更加容易。
for anyone that doesn't know is it's
对于不了解的人来说，钓鱼攻击是指
they send you something saying, uh, hi,
他们会给你发信息说：“嗨，
I'm your friend John and I'm stuck in El
我是你的朋友约翰，我被困在
Salvador. Could you just wire this
萨尔瓦多了。” 你能把
money? That's one kind of attack. But
钱电汇过来吗？ 那是一种攻击方式。 但这些
the fishing attacks are really trying to
钓鱼袭击者其实是想证明
get your loon credentials. And now with
你是疯子。 现在有了
AI, they can clone my voice, my image.
人工智能，他们可以克隆我的声音、我的图像。
They can do all that. I'm struggling at
他们可以做到这一切。 我
the moment because there's a bunch of AI
目前遇到了一些困难，因为
scams on X and also Meta. And there's
X 和 Meta 上有很多 AI 骗局。
one in particular on Meta, so Instagram,
尤其是在 Meta、Instagram 和
Facebook at the moment, which is a paid
Facebook 上，目前有一个付费
advert where they've taken my voice from
广告，他们盗用了我
the podcast. They've taken the my
播客中的声音。 他们模仿了我的举止，
mannerisms and they've made a new video
制作了一段新视频，视频里我
of me encouraging people to go and take
鼓励人们去
part in this crypto Ponzi scam or
参与这个加密货币庞氏骗局之
whatever. And we've been, you know, we
类的东西。 你知道，我们
spent weeks and weeks and weeks and
花了几个星期的时间，
weeks and end emailing Meta telling,
最后给 Meta 发邮件说：
"Please take this down." They take it
“请把它撤下来。” 他们把它
down, another one pops up. They take
撤下来，另一个又冒了出来。 他们把
that one down, another one pops up. So,
那个撤下来，另一个又冒出来。 所以，
it's like whack-a-ole. And then it's
这就像打地鼠游戏一样。 然后就
very annoying. The the heartbreaking
非常令人恼火了。 最令人心碎的
part is you get the messages from people
是，你会收到那些上当受骗的人发来的信息，
they've lost £500 or $500 and they cross
他们损失了 500 英镑或 500 美元，他们联系
with you cuz you recommended it and I'm
你是因为你推荐了它，我当时就觉得
I'm like I'm sad for them. It's very
我为他们感到难过。 真是太
annoying. Yeah. I have a a smaller
烦人了。 是的。 我有一个规模较小的
version of that which is PE some people
版本，也就是PE，现在有些人
now publish papers with me as one of the
以我为作者之一发表论文
authors. Mhm. And it looks like it's in
。 嗯。 看起来他们这样做是为了给
citations to themselves. Ah, so cyber
自己获得大量的引用次数。 啊，网络
attacks a very real threat. There's been
攻击确实是一个非常现实的威胁。 这类产品数量
an explosion of those. And these already
激增。 而且很
obviously AI is very patient. So they
明显，人工智能非常有耐心。 所以他们
can go through 100 million lines of code
可以检查 1 亿行代码，
looking for known ways of attacking
寻找已知的攻击方法
them. That's easy to do. But they're
。 这很容易做到。 但他们会变得
going to get more creative and they may
更有创造力，
some people believe and I some people
有些人相信，包括我在内的一些
who know a lot believe that maybe by
知情人士也相信，到
2030 they'll be creating new kinds of
2030 年，他们可能会创造出
cyber attacks which no person ever
前所未有的新型网络攻击
thought of. So that's very worrisome
。 所以这很令人担忧，
because they can think for themselves
因为他们能够独立思考，
and discover they can think for
并发现自己有独立思考的能力
themselves. They can draw new
。 他们可以从比任何人以往所见的都要
conclusions from much more data than a
多得多的数据中得出新的结论
person ever saw. Is there anything
。
you're doing to protect yourself from
你采取了哪些措施来保护自己免受
cyber attacks at all? Yes. It's one of
网络攻击？ 是的。 这是极
the few places where I changed what I do
少数我
radically because I'm scared of cyber
因为害怕网络
attacks. Canadian banks are extremely
攻击而彻底改变工作方式的地方之一。 加拿大银行非常
safe. In 2008, no Canadian banks came
安全。  2008年，没有一家加拿大银行濒临
anywhere near going bust. So, they're
破产。 所以，它们是
very safe banks because they're well
非常安全的银行，因为它们受到良好的
regulated, fairly well regulated.
监管，相当完善。
Nevertheless, I think a cyber attack
然而，我认为网络攻击
might be able to bring down a bank. Now,
有可能摧毁一家银行。 现在，
if you have all my savings are in shares
假设我的所有积蓄都投资于
in banks held by banks, so if the bank
银行持有的银行股票，那么即使银行
gets attacked and it holds your shares,
遭到攻击，持有你的股票，
they're still your shares. And so, I
这些股票仍然是你的。 所以，我
think you'd be okay unless the attacker
认为只要攻击者不
sells the shares because the bank can
出售股票，你就没问题，因为银行也可以
sell the shares. If the attacker sells
出售股票。 如果攻击者卖掉了
your shares, I think you're screwed. I
你的股票，我觉得你就完蛋了。 我
don't know. I mean, maybe the bank would
不知道。 我的意思是，银行或许会
have to try and reimburse you, but the
尝试赔偿你，但
bank's bust by now, right? So,
银行现在已经倒闭了，对吧？ 所以，
So I'm worried about a Canadian bank
我担心一家加拿大银行
being taken down by a cyber attack and
会因为网络攻击而倒闭，
the attacker selling selling shares that
攻击者会抛售该银行
it holds. So I spread my money and my
持有的股票。 因此，我把我和孩子们的钱分散存放
children's money between three banks in
在三家银行，因为我
the belief that if a cyber attack takes
相信，如果网络攻击导致
down one Canadian bank, the other
一家加拿大银行倒闭，其他
Canadian banks will very quickly get
加拿大银行很快就会变得
very careful. And do you have a phone
非常谨慎。 你有一部
that's not connected to the internet? Do
没有连接互联网的手机吗？
you have any like, you know, I'm
你有没有遇到过类似的问题，比如，你知道，我正在
thinking about storing data and stuff
考虑存储数据之类的
like that. Do you think it's wise to
。 你认为
consider having cold storage? I have a
考虑设置冷藏设施是明智之举吗？ 我有一个
little disc drive and I back up my
小型光驱，我把
laptop on this hard drive. So I actually
笔记本电脑的备份都放在这个硬盘上。 所以我的
have everything on my laptop on a hard
所有东西实际上都存在笔记本电脑的
drive. At least you know if the whole
硬盘里。 至少你知道，即使整个
internet went down I had the sense I
互联网瘫痪了，我的
still got it on my laptop and I still
笔记本电脑上仍然有网络，我
got my information. Okay. Then the next
的信息也还在。 好的。 接下来
thing is using AI to create nasty
就是利用人工智能制造恶性
viruses.
病毒。
Okay. And the problem with that is that
好的。 问题在于，这只
just requires one crazy guy with the
需要一个
grudge. One guy who knows a little bit
心怀怨恨的疯子就行了。 一个略懂
of molecular biology, knows a lot about
分子生物学，精通
AI, and just wants to destroy the world.
人工智能，却只想毁灭世界的人。
You can now create
现在
new viruses relatively cheaply using AI.
利用人工智能可以相对便宜地制造新病毒。
And you don't have to be a very skilled
而且你不需要成为一名技术非常精湛的
molecular biologist to do it. And that's
分子生物学家才能做到这一点。 那
very scary. So you could have a small
太可怕了。 例如，你可能会有一个小型
cult, for example.
邪教组织。
a small cult might be able to raise a
一个小型邪教组织或许能够筹集到
few million dollars. For a few million
几百万美元。 只要花几百万
dollars, they might be able to design a
美元，他们或许就能设计出
whole bunch of viruses. Well, I'm
一大堆病毒。 嗯，我
thinking about some of our foreign
想到的是我们的一些外国
adversaries doing government funded
对手在进行政府资助的
programs. I mean, there was lots of talk
项目。 我的意思是，当时有很多
around COVID and Woo the Wuhan
关于新冠病毒和武汉
laboratory and what they were doing and
实验室的讨论，以及他们在做什么和
gain a function research, but I'm
进行功能性研究，但我想知道，
wondering if in, you know, a China or a
在中国、
Russia or an Iran or something, the
俄罗斯、伊朗或其他国家，
government could fund a program for a
政府是否可以资助一个项目，让一
small group of scientists to make a
小群科学家制造一种
virus that they could, you know, I think
病毒，你知道，我认为
they could. Yes. Now, they'd be worried
他们可以做到。 是的。 现在，他们会担心
about retaliation. They'd be worried
遭到报复。 他们会担心
about other governments doing the same
其他国家的政府也会
to them. Hopefully, that would help keep
对他们采取同样的做法。 希望这样能有助于控制
it under control. They might also be
疫情。 他们可能也
worried about the virus spreading to
担心病毒会传播到
their country. Okay? Then there's um
他们的国家。 好的？ 然后还有
corrupting elections.
选举舞弊的问题。
So, if you wanted to use AI to corrupt
所以，如果你想利用人工智能来操纵
elections,
选举，
a very effective thing is to be able to
一个非常有效的方法就是
do targeted political advertisements
投放有针对性的政治广告，
where you know a lot about the person.
因为你对候选人有很多了解。
So anybody who wanted to use AI for
因此，任何想要利用人工智能
corrupting elections would try and get
操纵选举的人都会想方设法获取
as much data as they could about
尽可能多的选民数据
everybody in the electorate. With that
。
in mind, it's a bit worrying what Musk
考虑到这一点，马斯克
is doing at present in the States, going
目前在美国的所作所为有点令人担忧，他
in and insisting on getting access to
进入美国并坚持要获得
all these things that were very
所有这些被
carefully siloed. The claim is it's to
精心隔离的信息。 官方声称此举是为了
make things more efficient, but it's
提高效率，但
exactly what you would want if you
如果你
intended to corrupt the next election.
打算操纵下次选举，这正是你想要的。
How do you mean? Because you get all
你是什​​么意思？ 因为你可以获得所有
this data on the people. You get all
这些关于人们的数据。 你可以获得所有
this data on people. You know how much
这些关于人们的数据。 你知道
they make where they you know everything
他们赚多少钱，你对
about them. Once you know that, it's
他们的一切都了如指掌。 一旦你了解了这一点，就很
very easy to manipulate them because you
容易操纵他们，因为你
can make an AI that you can send
可以创建一个人工智能，向他们发送
messages um that they'll find very
一些他们会觉得很有
convincing telling them not to vote, for
说服力的信息，例如告诉他们不要投票
example.
。
So, I have no no reason other than
所以，除了常识之外，我没有其他理由这样
common sense to think this, but I
认为，但
wouldn't be surprised if part of the
如果
motivation of getting all this data from
从美国政府渠道获取所有这些数据的部分动机
American government sources is to
是为了
corrupt elections. Another part might be
操纵选举，我不会感到惊讶。 另一部分原因可能是，
that it's very nice training data for a
这是大型模型非常好的训练数据
big model, but he would have to be
，但他必须
taking that data from the government and
从政府那里获取这些数据并将
feeding it into his Yes. And what
其输入到他的模型中。是的。
they've done is turned off lots of the
他们关闭了很多
security controls, got rid of the some
安全控制措施，取消了一些用于
of the organization to protect against
防范此类攻击的组织架构
that. Um, so that's corrupting
。 嗯，这就是腐败
elections. Okay. Then there's creating
选举。 好的。 然后，像 YouTube 和 Facebook 这样的机构又制造了
these two echo chambers
这两个回音室，向
and Facebook showing people things that
人们展示一些
will make them indignant. People love to
会激起他们愤慨的内容。 人们喜欢
be indignant. Indignant as in angry or
义愤填膺。  “愤慨”是指生气吗？或者说，“
what does indignant mean? Feeling I'm
愤慨”是什么意思？ 我感觉有点
sort of angry but feeling righteous.
生气，但又觉得自己很正义。
Okay. So, for example, if you were to
好的。 例如，如果你给
show me something that said Trump did
我看一些资料，说特朗普做了
this crazy thing, here's a video of
这件疯狂的事，那么这里有一段
Trump doing this completely crazy thing.
特朗普做这件完全疯狂的事的视频。
I would immediately click on it.
我会立即点击它。
Okay. So, putting us in echo chambers
好的。 所以，这让我们陷入回音室效应，
and dividing us. Yes. And that's um the
分裂我们。 是的。 而这正是
policy that YouTube and Facebook and
YouTube、Facebook 和
others use for deciding what to show you
其他公司用来决定接下来向你展示什么内容的策略
next is causing that. If they had a
造成的。 如果他们奉行的是
policy of showing you balanced things,
展示平衡内容的政策，
they wouldn't get so many clicks and
他们就不会获得那么多点击量，也
they wouldn't be able to sell so many
卖不出那么多
advertisements.
广告。
And so it's basically the profit motive
所以，基本上就是逐利动机驱使人们向
is saying show them whatever will make
他们展示任何能让
them click. And what'll make them click
他们点击的内容。 而能让他们产生兴趣的，
is things that are more and more
是越来越
extreme. And that confirmed my existing
极端的事物。 这证实了我原有的
bias. That confirm my existing bias. So
偏见。 这证实了我原有的偏见。 所以
you're getting your biases confirmed all
你的偏见不断地得到证实，
the time further and further and further
而且越来越严重
and further, which means you're you're
，这意味着你正在
driving away, which is now there's in
远离彼此，现在在
the states there's two communities that
美国，有两个群体几乎
don't hardly talk to each other. I'm not
不互相交流。 我
sure people realize that this is
不确定人们是否意识到，
actually happening every time they open
每次打开
an app. But if you go on a Tik Tok or a
应用程序时实际上都会发生这种情况。 但是，如果你浏览 TikTok、
YouTube or one of these big social
YouTube 或其他大型社交
networks, the algorithm, as you you
网络，正如你
said, is designed to show you more of
所说，算法会向你展示更多
the things that you had interest in last
你上次感兴趣的内容
time. So, if you just play that out over
。 所以，如果你就这样持续
10 years, it's going to drive you
10 年，它会让你
further and further and further into
越来越固守
whatever ideology or belief you have and
你的意识形态或信仰，
further away from nuance and common
越来越远离细微差别、
sense and um parity, which is a pretty
常识和公平，这是一件非常
remarkable thing. I I like people don't
了不起的事情。 我喜欢人们不
know it's happening. They just open
知道这件事正在发生。 他们只是打开
their phones and experience something
手机，看到一些东西，就
and think this is the news or the
以为这就是新闻或者
experience everyone else is having.
其他人正在经历的事情。
Right. So, basically, if you have a
正确的。 所以，基本上，如果你有一份
newspaper and everybody gets the same
报纸，而且每个人都拿到同样的
newspaper, Yeah. you get to see all
报纸，是的。 你会看到
sorts of things you weren't looking for
各种各样你原本没想看的东西，
and you get a sense that if it's in the
你会觉得
newspaper it's an important thing or
报纸上刊登的都是重要或
significant thing but if you have your
意义重大的事情。但如果你用
own news feed my news feed on my iPhone
自己的新闻推送，比如我iPhone 3上的新闻推送，很多
3/arters of the stories are about AI and
新闻都跟人工智能有关。
I find it very hard to know if the whole
我很难判断
world's talking about AI all the time or
全世界是不是都在谈论人工智能，还是只有
if it's just my newsfeed
我的新闻推送这样。
okay so driving me into my echo chambers
好吧，这让我陷入了回音室效应，而
um which is going to continue to divide
这只会让
us further and further I'm actually
我们之间的分歧越来越大。我
noticing that the algorithm are becoming
注意到算法变得
even more,
越来越……
what's the word?
该怎么说呢？
Tailored. And people might go, "Oh,
量身定制。 人们可能会说：“哦，
that's great." But what it means is
那太好了。” 但这意味着
they're becoming even more personalized,
它们正变得越来越个性化，
which is means that my reality is
也就是说，我的现实与
becoming even further from your reality.
你的现实之间的距离越来越远。   是的
Yeah. It's crazy. We don't have a shared
。 太疯狂了。 我们已经不再拥有共同的
reality anymore. I share reality with
现实感了。 我与
other people who watch the BBC and other
观看 BBC 和其他
BBC news and other people who read the
BBC 新闻的人，以及
Guardian and other people who read the
阅读《卫报》和《
New York Times. I have almost no shared
纽约时报》的人共享着现实。 我
reality with people who watch Fox News.
和那些看福克斯新闻的人几乎没有任何共同的认知。   挺
It's pretty It's pretty um I I It's
漂亮的，挺漂亮的，嗯，我，我，这令人
worrisome. Yeah. Behind all this is the
担忧。 是的。 这一切背后都隐藏着一个
idea that these companies just want to
理念：这些公司只想
make profit and they'll do whatever it
赚钱，
takes to make more profit because they
为了赚取更多利润，他们会不择手段，因为他们
have to. They're legally obliged to do
不得不这样做。 他们有法律义务
that. So, we almost can't blame the
这样做。 所以，我们几乎不能责怪这家
company, can we? If they're if Well,
公司，对吧？ 如果他们是……好吧，
capitalism's done very well for us. It's
资本主义对我们来说确实很好。 它
produced lots of goodies. Yeah. But you
产出了很多好东西。 是的。 但你
need to have it very well regulated.
需要对其进行非常严格的监管。
So what you really want is to have rules
所以你真正想要的是制定一些规则，让
so that when some company is trying to
一些公司在追求
make as much profit as possible,
利润最大化时，
in order to make that profit, they have
为了获得利润，必须
to do things that are good for people in
做一些对大众有益的事情
general, not things that are bad for
，而不是做一些对大众有害的事情
people in general. So once you get to a
。 所以，一旦出现这种
situation where in order to make more
情况：为了获得更多
profit the company starts doing things
利润，公司开始做一些
that are very bad for society like
对社会非常有害的事情，比如向
showing you things that are more and
你展示
more extreme that's what regulations are
越来越极端的东西，这就是监管存在的意义
for. So you need regulations with
。 所以资本主义需要监管
capitalism. Now companies will always
。 现在企业总是会
say regulations get in the way make us
说，监管会阻碍我们，
less efficient and that's true. The
降低我们的效率，这确实如此。 制定
whole point of regulations is to stop
规章制度的全部意义就在于阻止
them doing things to make profit that
他们为了牟利而做出
hurt society. And we need strong
损害社会的事情。 我们需要强有力的
regulation. who's going to decide
监管。 谁来决定它
whether it hurts society or not because
是否会对社会造成伤害？因为
you know that's the job of politicians
你知道，这通常是政客的职责。
unfortunately if the politicians are
不幸的是，如果政客被
owned by the companies that's not so
公司收买，那就糟了。
good and also the politicians might not
而且，政客可能并不
understand the technology we you've
了解这项技术。你
probably seen the Senate hearings where
可能看过参议院的听证会，
they wheel out you know Mark Zuckerberg
他们会请出马克·扎克伯格
and these big tech CEOs and it is quite
和其他一些大型科技公司的首席执行官，这很
embarrassing because they're asking the
尴尬，因为他们问的
wrong questions well I've seen the video
问题都不对。我还看过
of the US education secretary talking
美国教育部长谈论
about how they're going to get AI in the
如何将人工智能引入
classrooms except she thought it was
课堂的视频，但她误以为人工智能
called A1
叫A1。
She's actually there saying we're going
她当时说，我们要让
to have all the kids interacting with
所有孩子都与
A1. There is a school system that's
A1互动。 有一个学校系统
going to start um making sure that first
即将开始，确保一
graders or even preks have A1 teaching,
年级甚至学前班的学生每年都能接受一流的教学，
you know, every year starting, you know,
你知道，从那么
that far down in the grades. And that's
低年级开始。 那真是一件
just a that's a wonderful thing.
很棒的事情。
[Laughter]
[笑声]
And these are what these are the people
这就是
that these are the people in charge.
当权者。
Ultimately the tech companies are in
最终，科技公司掌握了
charge because they will outsmart the
主动权，因为他们
tech companies in the states now at
现在比美国的科技公司更胜一筹。
least a few weeks ago when I was there
至少几周前我在那里的时候，
they were running an advertisement about
他们还在投放广告，说不应该
regulate AI because it would hurt us in
监管人工智能，因为这会损害我们在
the competition with China. Yeah. And
与中国的竞争中的地位。 是的。
that's a that's a plausible argument
这是一个合情合理的论点
there. Yes it will. But you have to
。 是的，会的。 但你必须
decide, do you want to compete with
做出决定，你是否想
China by doing things that will do a lot
通过做一些会对
of harm to your society? And you
你的社会造成巨大伤害的事情来与中国竞争？ 你
probably don't.
可能并不知道。
I guess they would say that it's not
我想他们会说，
just China, it's Denmark and Australia
不仅仅是中国，还有丹麦、澳大利亚、
and Canada and the UK. They're not so
加拿大和英国。 他们并不太
worried about and Germany. But if they
担心德国。 但如果他们
kneecap themselves with regulation, if
用监管束缚自己，如果
they slow themselves down, then the
他们放慢脚步，那么
founders, the entrepreneurs, the
创始人、企业家、
investors are going to go. I think
投资者就会离开。 我认为
calling it kneecapping is taking a
称之为“打断膝盖骨”是一种
particular point of view is take taking
特定的观点，即认为
the point of view that regulations are
监管是
sort of very harmful. What you need to
非常有害的。 你需要
do is just constrain the big companies
做的就是约束大公司，让
so that in order to make profit, they
它们为了盈利而
have to do things that are socially
去做对社会
useful. Like Google search is a great
有益的事情。 谷歌搜索就是一个很好的
example that didn't need regulation
例子，它不需要监管，
because it just made information
因为它只是让
available to people. It was great. But
人们能够获取信息。 太棒了。 但是，
then if you take YouTube which starts
如果你看看 YouTube，它开始向
showing you adverts and showing you more
你展示广告，并向你展示
and more extreme things that needs
越来越极端的内容，这就需要
regulation but we don't have the people
监管，但
to regulate it as we've identified. I
正如我们所发现的，我们没有足够的人手来监管它。 我
think people know pretty well um that
认为人们都很清楚，不断向
particular problem of showing you more
你展示
and more extreme things. That's a
越来越极端的事物会带来怎样的问题。 这是一个
well-known problem that the politicians
众所周知的问题，政客们都
understand. They just um need to get on
明白这一点。 他们只需要……赶紧着手
and regulate it. So that was the the
规范一下。 所以，
next point which was that the algorithms
下一个要点就是算法会让
are going to drive us further into our
我们更加深陷于
echo chambers, right?
回音室效应中，对吧？
What's next? Lethal autonomous weapons.
接下来是什么？ 致命的自主武器。
Lethal autonomous weapons.
致命的自主武器。
That means things that can kill you and
这意味着有些东西能够杀死你，并且
make their own decision about whether to
能够自行决定是否要
kill you, which is the great dream, I
杀死你。我
guess, of the military-industrial
想，这正是军工复合
complex being able to create such
体梦寐以求的，他们能够制造出这样的
weapons. So, the worst thing about them
武器。 所以，它们最糟糕的地方在于，
is big powerful countries always have
强大的大国总是有
the ability to invade smaller poorer
能力入侵较小较贫穷的
countries. they're just more powerful.
国家。 它们只是更强大而已。
But if you do that using actual
但如果你用真正的士兵这样做
soldiers, you get bodies coming back in
，就会有尸体被装在
bags and the relatives of the soldiers
袋子里运回来，阵亡士兵的家属肯定
who were killed don't like it. So you
不喜欢这样。 所以你就会
get something like Vietnam. Mhm. In the
得到类似越南那样的地方。 嗯。
end, there's a lot of protest at home.
最后，国内爆发了很多抗议活动。
If instead of bodies coming back in
如果运回来的不是装在
bags, it was dead robots, there'd be
袋子里的尸体，而是死去的机器人，那么
much less protest and the
抗议就会少得多，
military-industrial complex would like
军工复合体也会更喜欢这样，
it much more because robots are
因为机器人很
expensive. And suppose you had something
昂贵。 假设你有一个
that could get killed and was expensive
容易损坏且更换成本很高的东西
to replace. That would be just great.
。 那真是太好了。
Big countries can invade small countries
大国入侵小国要
much more easily because they don't have
容易得多，因为它们
their soldiers being killed. And the
的士兵不会伤亡。
risk here is that these robots will
这里的风险在于这些机器人可能会
malfunction or they'll just be more No,
发生故障，或者它们只会变得更加……不，
no, that's even if the robots do exactly
不，即使机器人完全按照
what the people who built the robots
制造它们的人的
want them to do, the risk is that it's
意愿行事，风险在于它会导致
going to make big countries invade small
大国
countries more often. More often because
更频繁地入侵小国。 更常见的情况是因为
they can Yeah. And it's not a nice thing
他们能够做到。是的。 这样
to do. So it brings down the friction of
做很不体面。 这样可以减少
war. It brings down the cost of doing an
战争摩擦。 这样可以降低入侵的成本
invasion.
。
And these machines will be smarter at
这些机器在战争中也会更加智能
warfare as well. So they'll be well even
。 所以即使
when the machines aren't smarter. So the
机器不再智能，他们也会安然无恙。 所以，
lethal autonomous weapons, they can make
他们现在可以制造致命的自主武器了
them now. And they I think all the big
。 我认为所有的大型
defense models are busy making them.
国防模型都在忙着制造它们。
Even if they're not smarter than people,
即使它们不如人类聪明，但
are still very nasty, scary things. Cuz
仍然是非常邪恶、可怕的东西。 因为
I'm thinking that, you know, they could
我在想，他们或许可以
show just a picture. Go get this guy.
只展示一张图片。 去把这家伙抓住。   是的
Yeah. And go take out anyone he's been
。 把他一直在
texting and this little wasp. So, two
发短信的那些人还有这只小黄蜂都干掉。
days ago, I was visiting a friend of
两天前，我去苏塞克斯拜访一位朋友，他
mine in Sussex who had a drone that cost
有一架价值
less than £200
不到 200 英镑的无人机，
and
然后
the drone went up. It took a good look
无人机就飞起来了。 它仔细地打量了
at me and then it could follow me
我一番，然后就跟着我
through the woods and it follow It was
穿过树林，一直跟着我。
very spooky having this drone. It was
有这架无人机在身边真是太可怕了。 它
about 2 meters behind me. It was looking
离我大约2米远。 它一直盯着
at me and if I moved over there, it
我看，如果我往那边挪，它也会往
moved over there. It could just track
那边挪。 它可能会跟踪
me. Mhm. For 200 pounds, but it was
我。 嗯。 虽然要200英镑，但它
already quite spooky. Yeah. And I
已经相当吓人了。 是的。 我
imagine there's as you say a race going
想正如你所说，现在肯定正在进行一场竞赛，看
on as we speak to who can build the most
谁能制造出最
complex autonomous autonomous weapons.
复杂的自主武器。
There is a a risk I often hear that some
我经常听到这样一种风险：
of these things will combine and the
这些因素可能会结合起来，导致
cyber attack will release weapons.
网络攻击释放武器。
Sure. Um you can you can get
当然。 嗯，你可以
combinatorily many risks by combining
通过组合
these other risks. Mhm. So, I mean, for
这些其他风险来获得组合式的多种风险。 嗯。 我的意思是，举个
example, you could get a super
例子，你可能会得到一个超级
intelligent AI that decides to get rid
智能的人工智能，它决定消灭
of people, and the obvious way to do
人类，而最直接的方法
that is just to make one of these nasty
就是制造一种这种可怕的
viruses. If you made a virus that was
病毒。 如果你制造出一种
very contagious, very lethal, and very
传染性极强、致命性极高、传播速度极慢的病毒
slow,
，那么在人们
realized what was happening. I mean, I
意识到发生了什么之前，每个人都会感染它。 我的意思是，我
think if a super intelligence wanted to
认为如果一个超级智能体想要
get rid of us, it will probably go for
消灭我们，它可能会选择
something biological like that that
类似这种
wouldn't affect it. Do you not think it
不会影响自身的生物学方法。 你不觉得这很可能会
could just very quickly turn us against
很快让我们反目成仇吗
each other? For example, it could send a
？ 例如，它可以向美国的
warning on the nuclear systems in
核系统发出警告，
America that there's a nuclear bomb
表明有
coming from Russia or vice versa and one
来自俄罗斯的核弹正在逼近，反之亦然，一方会
retaliates. Yeah. I mean, my basic view
进行报复。 是的。 我的意思是，我的基本观点
is there's so many ways in which the
是，
super intelligence could get rid of us.
超级智能有很多方法可以消灭我们。
It's not worth speculating about.
没必要对此进行猜测。
What What is What you have to do is
你必须做的就是
prevent it ever wanting to. That's what
阻止它有这种想法。 这才是
we should be doing research on. There's
我们应该研究的方向。
no way we're going to prevent it from
我们根本无法阻止它，
it's smarter than us, right? There's no
它比我们聪明，对吧？
rid of us if it wants to. We're not used
如果它想除掉我们，我们根本无法阻止。 我们不习惯
to thinking about things smarter than
思考比我们聪明的人或事物
us. If you want to know what life's like
。 如果你想知道
when you're not the apex intelligence,
当你不是最高智慧生物时，生活会是什么样子，那就去
ask a chicken.
问问鸡吧。   是的
Yeah. I was thinking about my dog Pablo,
。 今天早上出门的时候，我想起了我的狗帕布罗，
my French bulldog, this morning as I
我的法国斗牛犬
left home. He has no idea where I'm
。 他完全不知道我
going. He has no idea what I do, right?
要去哪里。 他根本不知道我是做什么的，对吧？   根本
Can't even talk to him. Yeah. And the g
没法跟他说话。 是的。 而
the intelligence gap will be like that.
智力差距也会如此。
So you're telling me that if I'm Pablo,
所以你的意思是，如果我是
my French bulldog, I need to figure out
我的法国斗牛犬巴勃罗，我就需要想
a way to make my owner not wipe me out.
办法让我的主人不要把我消灭掉。   是的
Yeah. So we have one example of that
。
which is mothers and babies. Evolution
母亲和婴儿就是一个例子。 进化论
put a lot of work into that. Mothers are
在这方面投入了大量精力。 母亲
smarter than babies, but babies are in
比婴儿聪明，但婴儿掌握着
control. And they're in control because
主动权。 他们之所以能控制局面，是因为
the mother just can't bear lots of
母亲无法忍受体内大量的
hormones and things, but the b the
激素和其他物质，但
mother just can't bear the sound of the
母亲也无法忍受
baby crying. Not all mothers. Not all
婴儿的哭声。 并非所有母亲。 并非所有
mothers. And then the baby's not in
母亲。 然后婴儿就失去了
control and then bad things happen. We
控制，然后就会发生不好的事情。 我们
somehow need to figure out how to make
必须想办法让
them not want to take over. The analogy
他们不想接管。
I often use is forget about
我经常用的比喻是，别管
intelligence, think about physical
智力，想想
strength. Suppose you have a nice little
体力。 假设你有一个漂亮的小
tiger cup. It's sort of bit bigger than
老虎杯。 它比猫稍微大一点
a cat. It's really cute.
。 它真可爱。
It's very cuddly, very interesting to
它非常可爱，也很有趣，
watch. Except that you better be sure
值得一看。 但你最好放心，
that when it grows up, it never wants to
它长大后绝对不会
kill you. Cuz if it ever wanted to kill
想杀你。 因为如果它真的想杀
you, you'd be dead in a few seconds. And
你，你几秒钟之内就会没命。
you're saying the AI we have now is the
你的意思是说，我们现在拥有的人工智能就是
target cub. Yep. And it's growing up.
目标幼崽。 是的。 它正在长大。   是的
Yep.
。
So, we need to train it as it's when
所以，我们需要像训练婴儿一样训练它
it's a baby. Well, now a tiger has lots
。 嗯，老虎身上有很多危险的基因
of in stuff built in. So, you know, when
。所以，你知道，
it grows up, it's not a safe thing to
它长大后，待在它身边并不安全
have around. But lions, people that have
。 但是狮子，或者把
lions as pets, yes. Sometimes the lion
狮子当作宠物的人，是的。 有时狮子对它
is affectionate to its creator but not
的创造者很亲昵，但对其
to others. Yes. And we don't know
他人却不然。 是的。 我们不知道
whether these AIs
这些人工智能是否会……
we we simply don't know whether we can
我们根本不知道我们能否
make them not want to take over and not
让它们不想接管我们的控制权，也
want to hurt us. Do you think we can? Do
不想伤害我们。 你觉得我们能做到吗？
you think it's possible to train super
你认为有可能训练出超级
intelligence? I don't think it's clear
智能吗？ 我认为目前还不清楚
that we can. So I think it might be
我们是否能够做到。 所以我觉得可能没
hopeless. But I also think we might be
希望了。 但我认为我们或许也能做到
able to. And it'd be sort of crazy if
。 如果因为
people went extinct cuz we couldn't be
我们懒得尝试而导致人类灭绝，那岂不是很疯狂吗？
bothered to try. If that's even a
如果这真的有
possibility, how do you feel about your
可能，你对自己的
life's work? Because you were Yeah. Um,
毕生事业有何感想？ 因为你就是。 嗯，
it sort of takes the edge off it,
这多少能缓解一下紧张的气氛，
doesn't it? I mean, the idea is going to
不是吗？ 我的意思是，这个想法
be wonderful in healthcare and wonderful
在医疗保健领域将会非常棒，
in education and wonderful. I mean, it's
在教育领域也会非常棒，真的非常棒。 我的意思是，这将
going to make call centers much more
大大提高呼叫中心的
efficient, though one worries a bit
效率，不过人们有点担心
job now do. It makes me sad. I don't
现在从事这项工作的人们的工作内容。 这让我很难过。 我并不
feel particularly guilty about
觉得
developing AI like 40 years ago because
40年前开发人工智能有什么特别的愧疚，因为当时
at that time we had no idea that this
我们根本不知道这
stuff was going to happen this fast. We
件事会发展得这么快。 我们当时
thought we had plenty of time to worry
觉得有足够的时间去担心这类
about things like that. They when you
事情。 当
when you can't get the to do much, you
你无法让它做太多事情的时候，你
want to get it to do a little bit more.
想让它多做一点。
You don't worry about this stupid little
你不用担心这个愚蠢的小
thing is going to take over from people.
东西会取代人类。
You just want it to be able to do a
你只是希望它能比
little bit more of the things people can
人类多做一些事情
do. It's not like I knowingly did
。 我并不是明知
something thinking this might wipe us
这样做可能会毁灭我们
all out, but I'm going to do it anyway.
所有人，但我还是要这么做。
Mhm. But it is a bit sad that it's not
嗯。 但令人有点遗憾的是，这并非
just going to be something for good.
一件好事。
So I feel I have a duty now to talk
所以我觉得我现在有责任谈谈这些
about the risks.
风险。
And if you could play it forward and you
如果你能推演未来，
could go forward 30, 50 years and you
推演 30 年、50 年，然后
found out that it led to the extinction
发现这导致了
of humanity and if that does end up
人类灭绝，如果这真的是最终
being the outcome,
结果，
well, if you played it forward and it
那么，如果你推演未来，发现这导致了
led to the extinction of humanity, I
人类灭绝，我
would use that to tell people to tell
会以此告诉人们，告诉
their governments that we really have to
他们的政府，我们真的必须
work on how we're going to keep this
努力研究如何
stuff under control. I think we need
控制这些东西。 我认为我们需要
people to tell governments that
有人告诉各国政府，
governments have to force the companies
政府必须强迫企业
to use their resources to work on safety
利用其资源来改善安全状况，
and they're not doing much of that
但他们并没有这样做，
because you don't make profits that way.
因为这样做无法盈利。
One of your your students we talked
我们之前谈到过的你的学生之一，
about earlier um Ilia Yep. Ilia left
嗯，伊利亚，是的。  Ilia离开了
OpenAI. Yep. And there was lots of
OpenAI。 是的。 很多人
conversation around the fact that he
议论纷纷，说他
left because he had safety concerns.
离开是因为出于安全考虑。   是的
Yes. And he's gone on to set set up a AI
。 之后，他又创办了一家人工智能
safety company. Yes.
安全公司。 是的。
Why do you think he left?
你觉得他为什么离开？
I think he left because he had safety
我认为他离开是因为他
concerns. Really? He um I still have
担心自身安全。 真的吗？ 我偶尔还会
lunch with him from time to time. His
和他一起吃午饭。 他的
parents live in Toronto. When he comes
父母住在多伦多。 他来
to Toronto, we have lunch together. He
多伦多的时候，我们会一起吃午饭。 他
doesn't talk to me about what went on at
从不跟我谈论
Open AI, so I have no inside information
OpenAI 内部发生的事情，所以我对此一无所知
about that. But I know I very well and
。 但我非常了解他，
he is genuinely concerned with safety.
他确实很关心安全问题。
So I think that's why he left because he
所以我认为这就是他离开的原因，因为他
was one of the top people. I mean he was
是公司高层之一。 我的意思是，他
he was probably the most important
可能是教会GPT开发过程中最重要的
person behind the development of um
人物，
church GPT the the early versions like
早期版本如
GPT2 he was very important in the
GPT2的开发对他影响很大。
development of that you know him
你认识他
personally so you know his character yes
本人，所以了解他的人品。是的，
he has a good moral compass he's not
他有很好的道德准则，不像
like someone like Musco has no moral
Musco那样没有道德
compass does Sam Alman have a good moral
准则。Sam Alman的道德准则好吗？
we'll see
我们拭目以待。
I don't know Sam so I don't want to
我不认识Sam，所以不想
comment on that. But from what you've
对此置评。 但就你所
seen, are you concerned about the
看到的，你是否对
actions that they've taken? Because if
他们采取的行动感到担忧？ 因为如果
you know Ilia and Ilia's a good guy and
你认识伊利亚，而伊利亚是个好人，而且
he's left
他离开了，
that would give you some insight. Yes.
那会给你一些启发。 是的。
It would give you some reason to believe
这会让你有理由相信那里存在
that there's a problem there. And if you
问题。 如果你
look at Sam's statements
看看萨姆
some years ago,
几年前的言论，
he sort of happily said in one interview
他在一次采访中似乎很高兴地说，
and this stuff will probably kill us
这些东西可能会害死我们
all. That's not exactly what he said,
所有人。 他并没有直接这么说，
but that's what it amounted to. Now he's
但意思差不多就是这样。 现在他
saying you don't need to worry too much
说你不用太担心
about it. And I suspect that's not
。 我怀疑这并非出于
seeking after the truth. That's driven
追求真相的动机。 这是出于
by seeking after money. Is it money or
对金钱的追求。 是金钱还是
is it power? Yeah. I shouldn't have said
权力？ 是的。 我不应该说
money. It's some some combination of
钱。 它是
those. Yes. Okay. I guess money is a
这些因素的某种组合。 是的。 好的。 我想金钱是
proxy for power. But I am I've got a
权力的象征。 但我有个
friend who's a billionaire and he is in
朋友是亿万富翁，他就在
those circles. And when I went to his
那个圈子里。 有一天我去他
house and had uh lunch with him one day,
家和他一起吃了顿午饭，
he knows lots of people in AI, building
他认识很多人工智能领域的人，这些人正在打造
the biggest AI companies in the world.
世界上最大的人工智能公司。
across the across his kitchen table in
在伦敦，他隔着厨房的餐桌给了我一个警告，让
London where he gave me an insight into
我了解到
the private conversations these people
这些人私下的谈话内容
have, not the media interviews they do
，而不是他们在媒体采访中
where they talk about safety and all
谈论安全等等
these things, but actually what some of
事情，而是
these individuals think is going to
这些人实际上认为将会
happen and what do they think is going
发生什么，以及他们认为将会
to happen. It's not what they say
发生什么。 这和他们公开宣称的不一样
publicly. You know, one one person who I
。 你知道，有一个人（我
shouldn't name who is the who is leading
不该点名），他领导着
world. He told me that he knows this
世界上最大的AI公司之一。 他告诉我他很了解这个
person very well and he privately thinks
人，并且私下里认为
that we're heading towards this kind of
我们正在走向一种反
dystopian world where we have just huge
乌托邦式的世界，在这个世界里，我们拥有大量的
amounts of free time. We don't work
空闲时间。 我们已经不工作了
anymore. And this person doesn't really
。 这个人根本不在乎这会对
going to have on the world. And this
世界造成什么伤害。
person who I'm referring to is building
我所指的这个人，正在打造
one of the biggest AI companies in the
全球最大的人工智能公司之一
world. And I then watch this person's
。 然后我上网观看这个人的
interviews online trying to figure out
采访，试图弄清楚他
which of three people it is. Yeah. Well,
是三个人中的哪一个。 是的。 嗯，
it's one of those three people. Okay.
是那三个人中的一个。 好的。
And I watch this person's interviews
我在网上观看这个人的采访，回
online and I I reflect on a conversation
想起我那位
who knows him and I go, "Fucking hell,
认识他的亿万富翁朋友和我之间的一次谈话，然后我说：“我的天哪，
this guy's lying publicly." Like, he's
这家伙竟然公开撒谎。” 就好像他
not telling the the truth to the world.
没有对全世界说出真相。
And that's haunted me a little bit. It's
这件事一直让我有点耿耿于怀。 这也是
part of the reason I have so many
为什么我
conversations around AR in this podcast
在这个播客里经常谈到增强现实（AR）的原因之一，
because I'm like, I don't know if
因为我觉得，我不知道
they're I think they're a some of them
它们是不是……我觉得它们中的一些有点
are a little bit sadistic about power. I
滥用权力。 我
think they they like the idea that they
认为他们喜欢那种能够
will change the world, that they will be
改变世界、能够从
the one that fundamentally shifts the
根本上改变
world. I think Musk is clearly like
世界的想法。 我觉得马斯克显然就是这样的人
that, right?
，对吧？
He's such a complex character that I
他是一个如此复杂的人物，
don't I don't really know how to place
我真的不知道该如何给
Musk. Um he's done some really good
马斯克贴标签。 嗯，他做了一些非常好的
things like um pushing electric cars.
事情，比如推广电动汽车。
That was a really good thing to do.
那真是件非常好的事。   是的
Yeah. Some of the things he said about
。 他关于
self-driving were a bit exaggerated, but
自动驾驶的一些说法有些夸张，但
he that was a really useful thing he
他确实做了一件非常有用的事情
did. Giving the Ukrainians communication
。 在
during the war with Russia. Stling. Um
与俄罗斯的战争期间，为乌克兰人提供通信保障。 斯特林。 嗯，
that was a really good thing he did.
他做的那件事真的很好。
there's a bunch of things like that. Um,
诸如此类的事情还有很多。 嗯，
but he's also done some very bad things.
但他同时也做过一些非常糟糕的事情。
So, coming back to this point of
那么，回到人工智能
the possibility of destruction
可能带来的破坏性影响
and the motives of these big companies,
以及这些大公司的动机这个问题上，
are you at all hopeful that anything can
你是否抱有任何希望，认为可以
be done to slow down the pace and
采取任何措施来减缓
acceleration of AI? Okay, there's two
人工智能的发展速度和加速进程？ 好的，这里有两个
issues. One is can you slow it down?
问题。 一是你能放慢速度吗？   是的
Yeah. And the other is, can you make it
。 另一个问题是，你能否确保
so it will be safe in the end? It won't
最终安全？ 它不会把
wipe us all out. I don't believe we're
我们全部消灭。 我不认为我们会
going to slow it down. Yeah. And the
放慢速度。 是的。
reason I don't believe we're going to
我不认为我们会
slow it down is because there's
放慢速度，因为
competition between countries and
国家之间存在竞争，
competition between companies within a
一个国家内部的公司之间也存在竞争，
country and all of that is making it go
所有这些都在
faster and faster. And if the US slowed
加速发展。 即使美国减缓了这一进程
it down, China wouldn't slow it down.
，中国也不会减缓。
Does IA think it's possible to make AI
人工智能认为有可能使人工智能
safe?
安全吗？
I think he does. He won't tell me what
我觉得他会的。 他不肯告诉我
his secret source is. I I'm not sure how
他的秘密消息来源是什么。 我不确定有
many people know what his secret source
多少人知道他的秘密消息来源
is. I think a lot of the investors don't
是什么。 我认为很多投资者并不
know what his secret source is, but
知道他的秘密资金来源，但
they've given him billions of dollars
他们仍然给了他数十亿美元，
anyway because they have so much faith
因为他们
in Asia, which isn't foolish. I mean, he
对亚洲充满信心，这并非愚蠢之举。 我的意思是，他
was very important in Alexet, which got
在 Alexet 项目中发挥了非常重要的作用，Alexet 实现了
object recognition working well. He was
良好的物体识别功能。 他是
things like GBC2
GBC2 等技术背后的主要推动者，而 GBC2
which then led to CH GPT.
又促成了 CH GPT 的诞生。
So I think having a lot of faith in IA
所以我认为对人工智能抱有极大的信心
is a very reasonable decision. There's
是一个非常合理的决定。
GPT2 which led rise to this whole
GPT-2 的创造者和主要推动者，正是他引发了这场
revolution left the company because of
革命，却因为安全原因离开了公司，这让人感到非常遗憾
safety reasons. He knows something that
。 他知道一些
I don't know about what might happen
我不知道的关于接下来可能发生的事情
next. Well, the company had now I don't
。 嗯，这家公司现在……我不
know the precise details um but I'm
知道具体细节，但我
fairly sure the company had indicated
相当肯定该公司曾表示，
that would it would use a significant
它将把相当
fraction of its resources of the compute
一部分计算资源
time for doing safety research and then
用于安全研究，然后
it kept then it reduced that fraction. I
它又减少了这个比例。 我
think that's one of the things that
认为那是发生的事情之一
happened. Yeah, that was reported
。 是的，这件事已经
publicly. Yes. Yeah.
公开报道了。 是的。 是的。
We've gotten to the autonomous weapons
我们已经讲到了
part of the risk framework. Right. So
风险框架中的自主武器部分。 正确的。
the next one is joblessness. Yeah. In
接下来就是失业问题了。 是的。
the past, new technologies have come in
过去，一些新技术出现后并
which didn't lead to joblessness. New
没有导致失业。 创造了新的
jobs were created. So the classic
就业机会。 人们最常用的
example people use is automatic tele
例子就是自动
machines. When automatic tele machines
电话机。 自动取款机
came in, a lot of bank tellers didn't
出现后，很多银行柜员并没有因此
lose their jobs. They just got to do
失业。 他们只是有机会去做
more interesting things. But here, I
更有趣的事情。 但我
think this is more like when they got
觉得这里的情况更像是
machines in the industrial revolution.
工业革命时期机器普及的时候。
you can't have a job digging ditches now
现在你不可能再找到挖沟的工作了，
because a machine can dig ditches much
因为机器挖沟
better than you can. And I think for
比你强得多。 我认为，对于
mundane intellectual labor, AI is just
枯燥乏味的脑力劳动，人工智能将会
going to replace everybody. Now, it will
取代所有人。 现在，这很可能表现
may well be in the form of you have
为
fewer people using air assistance. So
使用空中援助的人数减少。 所以，
assistant are now doing the work that 10
现在是由一个人和一个人工智能助手共同完成
people could do previously. People say
以前 10 个人才能完成的工作。 人们说
that it will create new jobs though, so
这将创造新的就业机会，所以
we'll be fine. Yes. And that's been the
我们应该没问题。 是的。
case for other technologies, but this is
其他技术也曾出现过这种情况，但这项
a very different kind of technology. If
技术却截然不同。 如果
it can do all mundane human intellectual
它能完成所有枯燥乏味的人类
labor,
脑力劳动，
then what new jobs is it going to
那么它又能创造什么新的就业机会呢
create? You'd you'd have to be very
？ 你必须拥有非常高的
skilled to have a job that it couldn't
技能才能胜任它无法
just do. So I don't I don't think
完成的工作。 所以我觉得
they're right. I think you can try and
他们的说法不对。 我认为你可以尝试
generalize from other technologies that
从其他
have come in like computers or automatic
已经出现的技术（例如计算机或自动
tele machines, but I think this is
遥控器）中进行概括，但我认为这是
different. People use this phrase. They
不同的。 人们会使用这个短语。 他们
say AI won't take your job. A human
说人工智能不会抢走你的工作。 人类
using AI will take your job. Yes, I
使用人工智能将会取代你的工作。 是的，我
think that's true. But for many jobs,
认为没错。 但对于很多工作来说，
that'll mean you need far fewer people.
这意味着需要的人员会大大减少。
My niece answers letters of complaint to
我侄女负责回复寄给
a health service. It used to take her 25
卫生部门的投诉信。 她以前需要25
minutes. She'd read the complaint and
分钟。 她读了投诉信，
she'd think how to reply and she'd write
想了想该如何回复，然后写了
a letter. And now she just scans it into
一封信。 现在她只需把它扫描到
um a chatbot and it writes the letter.
聊天机器人里，聊天机器人就会自动写信。
She just checks the letter. Occasionally
她只是查看了一下信件。
she tells it to revise it in some ways.
她偶尔会要求它在某些方面进行修改。
The whole process takes her five
整个过程只用了五
minutes. That means she can answer five
分钟。 这意味着她可以回复
times as many letters and that means
五倍的信件，也意味着
they need five times fewer of her so she
他们需要的她的人数减少五倍，所以她
can do the job that five of her used to
可以完成以前五个她才能完成的工作
do. Now, that will mean they need less
。 这意味着他们需要的
people. In other jobs, like in health
人手会减少。 在其他行业，例如医疗
care, they're much more elastic. So, if
保健行业，薪资待遇的弹性要大得多。 所以，如果
you could make doctors five times as
能让医生的
efficient, we could all have five times
效率提高五倍，我们就能
as much health care for the same price,
以同样的价格享受五倍的医疗保健，
and that would be great. There's there's
那就太好了。
people can absorb. They always want more
人们能够承受的医疗保健费用几乎没有上限。 如果不需要花钱，他们总是想要更多的
healthare if there's no cost to it.
医疗保健。
There are jobs where you can make a
有些工作，你可以让一个
person with an AI assistant much more
人借助人工智能助手来提高
efficient and you won't lead to less
效率，而且不会导致
people because you'll just have much
人手减少，因为
more of that being done. But most jobs I
更多的工作可以由人工智能助手来完成。 但我认为大多数工作
think are not like that. Am I right in
并非如此。 我的理解是否正确，
thinking the sort of industrial
工业
revolution
革命
played a role in replacing muscles? Yes.
在肌肉被取代的过程中发挥了作用？ 是的。
Exactly. And this revolution in AI
确切地。 人工智能的这场革命
replaces intelligence the brain. Yeah.
正在取代大脑的智能。 是的。
So, so mundane intellectual labor is
所以，枯燥乏味的脑力劳动就像
like having strong muscles and it's not
拥有强壮的肌肉一样，已经没什么
worth much anymore. So, muscles have
价值了。 所以，肌肉已经
been replaced. Now we intelligence is
被替换了。 现在我们的智能正在
being replaced. Yeah. So, what remains?
被取代。 是的。 那么，还剩下什么呢？
Maybe for a while some kinds of
或许在一段时间内，某些类型的
creativity but the whole idea of super
创造力会得到提升，但超级智能的概念将
intelligence is nothing remains. Um
不复存在。 嗯，
these things will get to be better than
这些东西
us at everything. So, what what do we
在所有方面都会比我们做得更好。 那么，
end up doing in such a world? Well, if
在这样的世界里，我们最终会做什么呢？ 如果
they work for us, we end up getting lots
他们为我们工作，我们最终就能毫不费力地获得大量的
of goods and services for not much
商品和服务
effort. Okay. But that sounds tempting
。 好的。 听起来很诱人，也很
and nice, but I don't know. There's a
不错，但我不知道。 这其中蕴含着一个
cautionary tale in creating more and
警示故事：人类为了追求便利而不断妥协，最终却可能适得其反
badly. Yes. And we need to figure out if
。 是的。 我们需要弄清楚
we can make it go well. So the the nice
我们能否让它顺利进行。 所以，比较理想的
scenario is imagine a company with a CEO
情况是，想象一家公司的首席执行官
who is very dumb, probably the son of
非常愚蠢，很可能是
the former CEO. And he has an executive
前任首席执行官的儿子。 他的行政
assistant who's very smart and he says,
助理非常聪明，他说：
"I think we should do this." And the
“我认为我们应该这样做。” 而
executive assistant makes it all work.
行政助理则让这一切顺利进行。
The CEO feels great. He doesn't
CEO感觉很好。 他不
understand that he's not really in
明白自己其实并没有
control. And in in some sense, he is in
掌控局面。 从某种意义上说，他
control. He suggests what the company
掌控着局面。 他提出了公司
should do. She just makes it all work.
应该采取的措施。 她总能把一切都安排妥当。
Everything's great. That's the good
一切都很好。 这是理想的
scenario. And the bad scenario, the bad
情况。
scenario, she thinks, "Why do we need
她心想，最糟糕的情况是，“我们为什么需要
him?"
他？”   是的
Yeah.
。
I mean, in a world where we have super
我的意思是，在一个我们拥有超级
intelligence, which you don't believe is
智能的世界里，而你却不认为那一天还很
that far away. Yeah, I think it might
遥远。 是的，我觉得可能离得
not be that far away. It's very hard to
不远。 很难
predict, but I think we might get it in
预测，但我认为我们可能在
like 20 years or even less. I made the
20年甚至更短的时间内就能实现。 因为女朋友的缘故，我
biggest investment I've ever made in a
向一家公司进行了有史以来最大的一笔投资
company because of my girlfriend. I came
。
home one night and my lovely girlfriend
一天晚上我回家时，我可爱的女朋友
was up at 1:00 a.m. in the morning
凌晨一点还在焦头烂额地
pulling her hair out as she tried to
为
piece together her own online store for
她自己的生意搭建网上商店
her business. And in that moment, I
。 就在那一刻，我
remembered an email I'd had from a guy
想起了之前收到的一封邮件，发件人是
called John, the founder of Stanto, our
John，他是Stanto的创始人，Stanto是我们
new sponsor and a company I've invested
新的赞助商，也是我投入
incredibly heavily in. And Standtore
巨资的公司。Stanto
helps creators to sell digital products,
帮助内容创作者通过个人简介中简单易用的可定制链接系统，销售数字产品、
courses, coaching, and memberships all
课程、辅导服务和会员资格
bio system. And it handles everything,
。 它能处理所有事情，包括
payments, bookings, emails, community
付款、预订、电子邮件、社区
engagement, and even links with Shopify.
互动，甚至还能与 Shopify 连接。
And I believe in it so much that I'm
我对此深信不疑，所以我要
going to launch a Stan challenge. And as
发起一项Stan挑战。 作为
part of this challenge, I'm going to
这项挑战的一部分，我将
give away $100,000 to one of you. If you
送出 10 万美元给你们中的一位。 如果你
want to take part in this challenge, if
想参加这项挑战，如果
you want to monetize the knowledge that
你想将
you have, visit stephenbartlet.stan
你所拥有的知识变现，请访问 stephenbartlet.stan
stan.store to sign up. And you'll also
stan.store 注册。 如果您使用该链接，您还
get an extended 30-day free trial of
可以获得 Stan Store 的 30 天免费试用期
Stan Store if you use that link. Your
。 坦白说，你的
next move could quite frankly change
下一步行动可能会改变
everything. Because I talked about
一切。 因为我
ketosis on this podcast and ketones, a
在这期播客节目中谈到了生酮和酮体，所以一个
brand called Ketone IQ sent me their
名为 Ketone IQ 的品牌给我寄来了他们的
little product here and it was on my
小产品，
desk when I got to the office. I picked
当我到办公室时，它就放在我的桌子上了。 我把它捡了起来
it up. It sat on my desk for a couple of
。 它在我的桌子上放了两个
weeks. Then one day, I tried it and
星期。 后来有一天，我试了一下，
honestly, I have not looked back ever
老实说，从那以后我就再也没后悔过
since. I now have this everywhere I go
。 现在我无论去哪里
when I travel all around the world. It's
旅行，都会随身携带它。 它
in my hotel room. My team will put it
在我的酒店房间里。 我的团队会把它放在
there. Before I did the podcast
那里。 今天我录制播客节目之前（
recording today that I've just finished,
刚刚录制完成），
I had a shot of Ketone IQ. And as is
我喝了一小杯 Ketone IQ。
always the case when I fall in love with
每当我爱上
a product, I called the CEO and asked if
一款产品时，我都会像往常一样打电话给首席执行官，询问
I could invest a couple of million quid
我是否可以
into their company. So, I'm now an
向他们的公司投资几百万英镑。 所以，我现在既是这家
investor in the company as well as them
公司的投资者，也是他们的
being a brand sponsor. I find it so easy
品牌赞助商。 我发现，喝了这种饮料后，很容易就能进入
to drop into deep focused work when I've
深度专注的工作状态
had one of these. I would love you to
。 我希望你能
try one and see the impact it has on
尝试一下，看看它对
you, your focus, your productivity, and
你、你的专注力、你的工作效率和
your endurance. So, if you want to try
你的耐力会产生怎样的影响。 所以，如果您今天就想尝试一下
it today, visit ketone.com/stephven
，请访问 ketone.com/stephven，
for 30% off your subscription. Plus,
即可享受订阅 30% 的折扣。 此外，
you'll receive a free gift with your
您的第二批货物还将附赠一份免费礼品
second shipment. That's
。 那是
ketone.com/stephven.
ketone.com/stephven。
I'm excited for you. I am. So, what's
我为你感到兴奋。 我是。 那么，
the difference between what we have now
我们现在拥有的智能
and super intelligence? Because it seems
与超级智能之间有什么区别？ 因为我觉得
use like chatbt3 or Gemini or Okay. So
使用 chatbt3、Gemini 或 Okay 之类的软件时，它真的很智能。 所以，
it's already AI is already better than
人工智能
us at a lot of things in particular
在很多方面，
areas like chess for example. Yeah. AI
尤其是在国际象棋等领域，已经比我们做得更好了。 是的。 人工智能
is so much better than us that people
比我们人类强大得多，人类
will never beat those things again.
再也无法战胜它们了。
Maybe the occasional win but basically
或许偶尔能赢一次，但基本上
they'll never be comparable again.
他们再也无法相提并论了。
Obviously the same in go in terms of the
显然，他们在围棋方面也
amount of knowledge they have. Um
拥有同样的知识水平。 嗯，
something like GBT4 knows thousands of
像GBT4这样的系统知道的
times more than you do. There's a few
比你多几千倍。
areas in which your knowledge is better
在某些领域，你的知识
than its and in almost all areas it just
比它强；而在几乎所有领域，它都比
knows more than you do. What areas am I
你懂得多。 我在哪些方面
better than it? Probably in interviewing
比它做得更好？ 可能是在面试
CEOs. You're probably better at that.
CEO的时候。 你在这方面可能更擅长。
You've got a lot of experience at it.
你在这方面经验丰富。
You're a good interviewer. You know a
你是一位优秀的面试官。 你
lot about it. If you tried if you got
对这方面了解很多。 如果你尝试让
GPT4 to interview a CEO, probably do a
GPT-4 去采访一位 CEO，结果可能
worse job. Okay.
更糟。 好的。
I'm trying to think if that if I agree
我正在思考我是否同意
with that statement. Uh GPT4 I think for
这种说法。 嗯，我觉得
sure. Yeah. Um but I but I guess you
肯定是GPT4。 是的。 嗯，不过我想你
could but it may not be long before
可以，但可能不久之后就会是的
Yeah. I guess you could train one on
。 我想你可以训练一个人学习
this how I ask questions and what I do
我提问的方式和做法，
and Sure. And if you took a general
当然可以。 如果你采用一个
purpose sort of foundation model and
通用的基础模型，
then you trained it up on not just you
然后不仅用你自己的数据，
but every every interviewer you could
还要用你能找到的每一个进行类似面试的面试官的数据，
especially you. You'll probably get to
尤其是你这样的面试官的数据来训练它。 你或许能把
be quite good at doing your job but
工作做得相当出色，但
probably not as good as you for a while.
可能暂时还不如以前的自己。
Okay. So, there's a few areas left and
好的。 所以，还有一些领域需要探索，而
then super intelligence becomes when
当超级智能
it's better than us at all things. When
在所有方面都优于我们时，它就变成了超级智能。
it's much smarter than you and almost
它比你聪明得多，几乎
all things is better than you. Yeah. And
所有事物都比你强。 是的。
you you you say that this might be a
你说这可能还需要
decade away or so. Yeah. It might be. It
十年左右的时间。 是的。 有可能。
might be even closer. Some people think
可能差距更小。 有些人认为实际距离更
it's even closer and might well be much
近，甚至可能
further. It might be 50 years away.
更远。 可能还要50年。
That's still a possibility. It might be
这仍然是一种可能性。 或许正是因为
that somehow training on human data
用人类数据进行训练，才
limits you to not being much smarter
使得你无法
than humans. My guess is between 10 and
比人类聪明多少。 我估计在未来10到
20 years we'll have super intelligence.
20年内，我们将拥有超级智能。
On this point of joblessness, it's
关于失业这个问题，
something that I've been thinking a lot
我一直在思考，
about in particular because I started
尤其是我开始
messing around with AI agents and we
研究人工智能代理之后。今天早上，我们
released an episode on the podcast
在播客上发布了一期节目，
actually this morning where we had a
我们和
of a big AI agent company and a few
一家大型人工智能代理公司的首席执行官以及
other people and it was the first moment
其他几位嘉宾就人工智能代理展开了讨论。
able in the interview to tell this agent
在采访中，我让这个代理帮
to order all of us drinks and then 5
我们所有人点饮料，5
minutes later in the interview you see
分钟后，你看到
the guy show up with the drinks and I
他端着饮料出现了，而我什么
didn't touch anything. I just told it to
都没动。那一刻，我突然灵光一闪，看到了未来可能的样子。 我只是让它帮
order us drinks to the studio. And you
我们订饮料送到工作室。 而且你
didn't know about who you normally got
也不知道你平时是从谁那里买
your drinks from. It figured that out
饮料的。 这是它
from the web. Yeah, figured out cuz it
从网上查到的。 是的，我搞清楚了，因为它
went on Uber Eats. It has my my my data,
出现在了 Uber Eats 上。 我想，里面应该有我的个人数据
I guess. And it I we put it on the
。 而且我们把它
screen in real time so everyone at home
实时显示在屏幕上，这样家里的每个人都
could see the agent going through the
可以看到代理商通过
internet, picking the drinks, adding a
互联网选​​择饮料，
tip for the driver, putting my address
给司机添加小费，输入我的地址
in, putting my credit card details in,
，输入我的信用卡信息，
and then the next thing you see is the
然后接下来你就会看到
drinks show up. So that was one moment.
饮料送到了。 那是其中的一个瞬间。
And then the other moment was when I
还有一次，我
used a tool called Replet and I built
使用了一个叫做 Replet 的工具，
software by just telling the agent what
通过告诉代理
I wanted. Yes. It's amazing, right? It's
我想要什么来构建软件。 是的。 太神奇了，对吧？ 这
amazing and terrifying at the same time.
既令人惊叹又令人恐惧。   是的
Yes. Because and if it can build
。 因为它能够开发出
software like that, right? Yeah.
那样的软件，对吧？ 是的。
Remember that the AI when it's training
请记住，人工智能在训练过程中
is using code and if it can modify its
使用的是代码，如果它能够修改
own code
自己的代码，
then it gets quite scary, right? because
那就相当可怕了，对吧？ 因为
it can modify. It can change itself in a
它能够修改。 它可以以
way we can't change ourselves. We can't
我们无法改变的方式改变自身。 我们无法
change our innate endowment, right?
改变与生俱来的天赋，对吧？   它
There's nothing about itself that it
自身没有任何
couldn't change.
改变不了的东西。
On this point of joblessness, you have
在失业这件事上，你还有
kids. I do. And they have kids. No, they
孩子。 我愿意。 他们也有孩子。 不，他们
don't have kids. No grandkids yet. What
没有孩子。 目前还没有孙辈。
their career prospects in a world of
在一个超级智能的世界里，你会如何向人们描述他们的职业前景
super intelligence? What should we we be
？ 我们应该
thinking about? Um, in the meantime, I'd
思考些什么？ 嗯，与此同时，我
say it's going to be a long time before
认为它还需要很长时间才能在
it's as good at physical manipulation as
物理操控方面达到
us. Okay. And so, a good bet would be to
我们这样的水平。 好的。 所以，当
be a plumber.
一名水管工应该是个不错的选择。
until the humanoid robots show up in
直到人形机器人出现在
such a world where there is mass
这样一个世界，大规模
joblessness which is not something that
失业——这并非可以
you just predict but this is something
预测的事情，但这是
that Sam Alman open AI I've heard him
开源人工智能的萨姆·阿尔曼（Sam Alman）预测过的，我也听过
predict and many of the CEOs Elon Musk I
许多首席执行官，包括埃隆·马斯克（Elon Musk）的预测。我
watched an interview which I'll play on
看过一段采访，里面有人
screen of him being asked this question
问了他这个问题，我会在屏幕上播放。
and it's very rare that you see Elon
你很少会看到埃隆·
Musk silent for 12 seconds or whatever
马斯克沉默12秒（或其他时间），
it was and then he basically says
然后他基本上说，
something about he actually is living in
他实际上生活在一种“
suspended disbelief i.e. He's basically
暂停怀疑”的状态中，也就是说，他基本上
just not thinking about it. When you
没有考虑过这个问题。 当你在
think about advising your children on a
考虑如何为孩子选择职业时，考虑到职业环境瞬息万变
career with so much that is changing,
，
what do you tell them is going to be of
你会告诉他们哪些信息才是真正
value?
有价值的？
Well,
嗯，
that is a tough question to answer. I
这个问题很难回答。 我
would just say, you know, to to sort of
只想说，要
follow their heart in terms of what they
跟随自己的内心，
they find um interesting to do or
去做自己觉得有趣或有
fulfilling to do. I mean, if I think
成就感的事情。 我的意思是，如果我
about it too hard, frankly, it can be uh
仔细想这件事，坦白说，可能会让人感到沮丧
dispariting and uh demotivating. Um
和气馁。 嗯，
because I mean, I I go through I mean I
因为我的意思是，我经历了很多，
I I've put a lot of blood, sweat, and
我投入了大量的心血和
tears into building the companies and
汗水来创建公司，
then it and then I'm like, wait, should
然后我就想，等等，
I be doing this? Because if I'm
我应该这样做吗？ 因为如果我
sacrificing time with friends and family
牺牲了与朋友和家人相处的时间，而
that I would prefer to to to but but
我更愿意这样做，但
then ultimately the AI can do all these
最终人工智能可以做所有这些
things. Does that make sense? I I don't
事情。 这样说得通吗？ 我不
know. Um to some extent I have to have
知道。 嗯，在某种程度上，我必须
deliberate suspension of disbelief in
刻意地放弃怀疑，
order to to remain motivated. Um so I I
才能保持动力。 嗯，所以我
guess I would say just you know
想说，你应该去做那些
work on things that you find
你觉得
interesting, fulfilling and um and and
有趣、有成就感，并且能为
of society. Yeah. A lot of these threats
社会做出贡献的事情。 是的。 很多这类威胁，从
it's very hard to intellectually you can
理智上
see the threat but it's very hard to
看得出来，但从
come to terms with it emotionally.
情感上却很难接受。   是的
Yeah. I haven't come to terms with it
。 我还没能从
emotionally yet. What do you mean by
情感上接受这件事。 你这话是什么意思
that?
？
I haven't come to terms with what the
我还没能接受
development of super intelligence could
超级智能的发展会对
do to my children's future.
我孩子的未来造成什么影响。
I'm okay. I'm 77.
我没事。 我77岁了，
I'm going to be out of here soon. But
很快就要离开这里了。 但是
for my children and my my younger
对于我的孩子、我的年轻
friends, my nephews and nieces and their
朋友、我的侄子侄女和他们的
children, um
孩子，嗯，
I just don't like to think about what
我实在不愿去想可能会
could happen.
发生什么。
Why? Cuz it could be awful.
为什么？ 因为情况可能会很糟糕。
In In what way?
以何种方式？
Well, if I ever decided to take over. I
嗯，如果我决定接管的话。 我的
mean, it would need people for a while
意思是，在
designed better analog machines to run
设计出更好的模拟机器来运行
the power stations. There's so many ways
发电站之前，还需要一段时间有人来运行这些发电站。 它有很多方法
it could get rid of people, all of which
可以除掉人类，
would of course be very nasty.
当然，所有这些方法都非常恶劣。
Is that part of the reason you do what
这是你现在所做事情的部分原因吗
you do now? Yeah. I I mean, I think we
？ 是的。 我的意思是，我认为我们
should be making a huge effort right now
现在应该全力以赴，努力
to try and figure out if we can develop
弄清楚我们是否能够
it safely. Are you concerned about the
安全地开发它。 您是否担心
midterm impact potentially on your
中期选举可能会对您的
nephews and your your kids in terms of
侄子和孩子的
their jobs as well? Yeah, I'm concerned
工作产生影响？ 是的，我担心
about all that. Are there any particular
所有这些问题。
industries that you think are most at
您认为哪些行业面临的
risk? People talk about the creative
风险最大？ 人们经常谈论创意
industries a lot and sort of knowledge
产业和知识型
work. They talk about lawyers and
工作。 他们会谈论律师、
accountants and stuff like that. Yeah.
会计师之类的东西。 是的。
So, that's why I mentioned plumbers. I
所以，这就是我提到水管工的原因。 我
think plumbers are less at risk. Okay,
认为水管工的风险较小。 好吧，
I'm going to become a plumber. Someone
我要去当一名水管工。
like a legal assistant, a parallegal.
类似法律助理、律师助理之类的人。
Um they're not going to be needed for
嗯，它们不会
very long. And is there a wealth
长期需要。 这
inequality issue here that will will
会引发财富不平等问题吗
arise from this? Yeah, I think in a
？ 是的，我认为在一个
society which shared out things fairly,
资源分配公平的社会里，
if you get a big increase in
如果生产力大幅提高
productivity, everybody should be better
，每个人都应该
off.
受益。
But if you can replace lots of people by
但是，如果用AIS取代很多人
AIS,
，
then the people who get replaced will be
那么被取代的人处境会
worse off
更糟，
and the company that supplies the AIS
而提供AIS的公司
and the company that uses the AIS. So
和使用AIS的公司则会获益匪浅。 所以
it's going to increase the gap between
这将加剧
rich and poor. And we know that if you
贫富差距。 我们知道，如果你
look at that gap between rich and poor,
观察贫富差距，就能
that basically tells you how nice the
大致了解一个社会有多好
society is. If you have a big gap, you
。 如果社会存在巨大鸿沟，就会
get very nasty societies in which people
出现非常糟糕的社会，人们
live in world communities and put other
生活在世界社区中，并将其他
people in mass jails. It's not good to
人关进大规模监狱。
increase the gap between rich and poor.
加剧贫富差距并非好事。
The International Monetary Fund has
国际货币基金组织对
generative AI could cause massive labor
生成式人工智能可能导致大规模劳动力市场
disruptions and rising inequality and
动荡和不平等加剧表示深切担忧，并
has called for policies that prevent
呼吁制定政策防止
this from happening. I read that in the
这种情况发生。 我是从
business insider. So, have they given
商业内幕网站上看到的。 那么，他们有没有给出
any of what the policies should look
任何关于政策具体内容的建议呢
like? No. Yeah, that's the problem. I
？ 不，没错，这就是问题所在。 我的
mean, if AI can make everything much
意思是，如果人工智能能够让一切变得
more efficient and get rid of people for
更加高效，并取代
most jobs or have a person assisted by I
大多数人的工作，或者让一个人在人工智能的帮助下
doing many many people's work, it's not
完成很多人的工作，那么我们该如何应对呢？
obvious what to do about it. It's
这是
universal basic income,
全民基本收入，
give everybody money. Yeah, I I I think
给每个人都发钱。 是的，我认为
that's a good start and it stops people
这是个好的开始，可以阻止人们
starving. But for a lot of people, their
挨饿。 但对很多人来说，
dignity is tied up with their job. I
尊严与他们的工作息息相关。 我的
mean, who you think you are is tied up
意思是，你认为自己是谁，
with you doing this job, right? Yeah.
与你从事这份工作息息相关，对吧？ 是的。
And if we said, "We'll give you the same
如果我们说，“我们会给你同样的
money just to sit around," that would
钱，让你闲着”，那会
impact your dignity. You said something
损害你的尊严。 你
earlier about it surpassing or being
之前说过它超越或
superior to human intelligence. A lot of
优于人类智能。
people, I think, like to believe that AI
我认为，很多人都喜欢相信人工智能只是
is is on a computer and it's something
电脑里的一个程序，
you can just turn off if you don't like
如果你不喜欢它，可以随时把它关掉
it. Well, let me tell you why I think
。 让我来告诉你为什么我认为
it's superior. Okay. Um, it's digital.
它更胜一筹。 好的。 嗯，它是数字化的。
And because it's digital, you can have
而且因为它是数字化的，所以
you can simulate a neural network on one
你可以在一台硬件上模拟神经网络
piece of hardware. Yeah. And you can
。 是的。 你可以
on a different piece of hardware. So you
在不同的硬件上模拟完全相同的神经网络。 所以你
can have clones of the same
可以拥有相同智能的克隆体
intelligence.
。
Now you could get this one to go off and
现在你可以让这个程序去
look at one bit of the internet and this
查看互联网的某一部分，让
other one to look at a different bit of
另一个程序去查看互联网的另一部分
the internet. And while they're looking
。 当他们浏览
at these different bits of the internet,
互联网上的这些不同内容时，
they can be syncing with each other. So
他们可以互相同步。 所以
they keep their weights the same, the
它们的重量保持不变，
connection strengths the same. Weights
连接强度也保持不变。 重量
are connection strengths. Mhm. So this
是连接强度的体现。 嗯。 所以这个
one might look at something on the
人可能会在网上看到一些东西，
internet and say, "Oh, I'd like to
然后说：“哦，我想
connection a bit." And it can convey
稍微增强一下这个连接的强度。” 它可以
that information to this one. So it can
将该信息传递给这个设备。 所以，
a bit based on this one's experience.
根据这个人的经验，它可以稍微增强这种联系的强度。
And when you say the strength of the
当你谈到联系的强度时
connection, you're talking about
，你指的是
learning. That's learning. Yes. Learning
学习。 这就是学习。 是的。 学习
consists of saying instead of this one
就是用另一种方式表达，比如
giving 2.4 four votes for whether that
用 2.4 票来决定是否
one should turn on. We'll have this one
开启某个功能。 我们将让这位用户
give 2.5 votes for whether this one
投出 2.5 票，决定是否开启此功能
should turn on. And that will be a
。 那也算是需要
little bit of learning. So these two
学习一些东西吧。 因此，
different copies of the same neural net
同一个神经网络的这两个不同副本
are getting different experiences.
获得了不同的体验。
They're looking at different data, but
他们研究的是不同的数据，但
they're sharing what they've learned by
他们通过对
averaging their weights together. Mhm.
各自的权重取平均值来分享他们所学到的知识。 嗯。
And they can do that averaging at like a
他们可以进行这种平均，就像
you can average a trillion weights. When
你可以对一万亿个重量进行平均一样。 当
you and I transfer information, we're
你我传递信息时，我们只能得到
a sentence. And the amount of
一句话的信息量。
information in a sentence is maybe a 100
一句话的信息量大概是100
bits. It's very little information.
比特。 信息量非常少。   我们
10 bits a second. These things are
每秒能传输 10 比特就算幸运了。 这些设备
transferring trillions of bits a second.
每秒传输数万亿比特。
So, they're billions of times better
所以，他们
than us at sharing information.
在信息共享方面比我们强数十亿倍。
And that's because they're digital. And
那是因为它们是数字化的。
you can have two bits of hardware using
您可以使用完全相同的方式，利用连接强度为两台硬件供电
same way. We're analog and you can't do
。 我们是模拟时代的，你不能
that. Your brain's different from my
那样做。 你的大脑和我的
brain. And if I could see the connection
大脑不一样。 即使我能看到
strengths between all your neurons, it
你所有神经元之间的连接强度，也对
wouldn't do me any good because my
我没有任何帮助，因为我的
neurons work slightly differently and
神经元工作方式略有不同，
they're connected up slightly
它们的连接方式也略有
differently. Mhm. So when you die, all
不同。 嗯。 所以当你死去的时候，
your knowledge dies with you. When these
你所有的知识也会随之消失。 当这些
things die, suppose you take these two
东西死亡时，假设你取出这两个
each other and you destroy the hardware
互为克隆的数字智能体，然后摧毁
they run on. As long as you've stored
它们运行的​​硬件。 只要你把
the connection strength somewhere, you
连接强度信息存储在某个地方，你就
can just build new hardware that
可以构建
executes the same instructions. So,
执行相同指令的新硬件。 这样，
it'll know how to use those connection
它就知道如何利用这些连接
strengths and you've recreated that
优势，而你也重新创造了这种
intelligence. So, they're immortal.
智能。 所以，他们是永生的。
We've actually solved the problem of
我们其实已经解决了永生的问题
immortality, but it's only for digital
，但这仅限于数字
things. So, it knows it will essentially
领域。 所以，它知道自己基本上会
know everything that humans know but
知道人类所知道的一切，而且会知道
more because it will learn new things.
更多，因为它还会学习新事物。
It will learn new things. It would also
它会学习新事物。 它还能
see all sorts of analogies that people
看到人们
probably never saw.
可能从未看到的各种类比。
So, for example, at the point when GPT4
例如，当 GPT4
couldn't look on the web, I asked it,
无法上网时，我问它：
"Why is a compost heap like an atom
“为什么堆肥堆像
bomb?"
原子弹？”
Off you go. I have no idea. Exactly.
走吧。 我不知道。 确切地。
Excellent. Most that's exactly what most
出色的。 大多数
people would say. It said, "Well, the
人都会这么说。 它说：“嗯，
time scales are very different and the
时间尺度非常不同，
energy scales are very different." But
能量尺度也非常不同。” 但
then I went on to talk about how a
后来我又继续谈到，
compost he as it gets hotter generates
堆肥温度越高，产生的
heat faster and an atom bomb as it
热量就越多；
produces more neutrons generates
原子弹产生中子越多，产生的
neutrons faster. And so they're both
中子也越多。 所以它们都是
chain reactions but at very different
链式反应，但发生的
time in energy scales. And I believe
时间在能量尺度上却截然不同。 我相信
GPT4 had seen that during its training.
GPT4 在训练过程中已经见过这种情况。
It had understood the analogy between a
它理解了
compost heap and an atom bomb. And the
堆肥堆和原子弹之间的类比。
reason I believe that is if you've only
我相信这一点的原因是，即使你
got a trillion connections, remember you
只有一万亿个连接，记住你
have 100 trillion. And you need to have
还有一千亿个连接。 你需要拥有
thousands of times more knowledge than a
比普通人多几千倍的知识
person, you need to compress information
，你需要将信息压缩
into those connections. And to compress
到这些联系中。 要压缩
information, you need to see analogies
信息，你需要看到
between different things. In other
不同事物之间的类比。
words, it needs to see all the things
换句话说，它需要看到所有
that are chain reactions and understand
连锁反应，理解
the basic idea of a chain reaction and
连锁反应的基本概念，并编写代码来
code that code the ways in which they're
描述它们之间的
different. And that's just a more
差异。 而且，这种
efficient way of coding things than
方式比
coding each of them separately.
分别编写每个代码更高效。
So it's seen many many analogies
所以它看到了许多很多类比，
probably many analogies that people have
可能有很多类比是人们
never seen. That's why I also think that
从未见过的。 所以我认为，
people who say these things will never
说这些话的人永远不会
be creative. They're going to be much
有创造力。 他们会比
more creative than us because they're
我们更有创造力，因为他们会
going to see all sorts of analogies we
看到我们
never saw. And a lot of creativity is
从未见过的各种类比。 很多创造力都
about seeing strange analogies.
来自于发现奇特的类比。
People are somewhat romantic about the
人们对
specialness of what it is to be human.
人类的特殊性抱有一些浪漫情怀。
And you hear lots of people saying it's
你经常会听到有人说情况
very very different. It's a it's a
非常非常不同。 这是一台
computer. We are, you know, we're
电脑。 你知道，我们是有
conscious. We are creatives. We we have
意识的。 我们是创意人士。 我们拥有
that the computers will never have. What
计算机永远无法企及的这种与生俱来的独特能力。
do you say to those people? I'd argue a
你想对这些人说什么？ 我
bit with the innate. Um,
对此先天论持保留意见。 嗯，
the first thing I say is we have a long
首先我要说的是，我们一直
history of believing people were
以来都相信人是
special. And we should have learned by
特殊的。 我们现在本应该吸取教训了
now. We thought we were at the center of
。 我们当时以为自己身处
the universe. We thought we were made in
宇宙的中心。 我们曾以为自己是按照
the image of God. white people thought
上帝的形象创造的。 白人认为
they were very special. We just tend to
自己非常特殊。 我们总是倾向于
want to think we're special.
认为自己很特别。
My belief is that more or less everyone
我认为，几乎每个人对
has a completely wrong model of what the
心智的理解都完全错误
mind is. Let's suppose I drink a lot or
。 假设我喝了很多酒，或者
I drop some acid and not recommended and
服用了一些不推荐的迷幻药，然后
I
我
say to you I have the subjective
说我主观上
experience of little pink elephants
感觉看到一些粉红色的小象
floating in front of me. Mhm. Most
漂浮在我面前。 嗯。 大多数
people
人
interpret that as there's some kind of
认为，人内心有一个
inner theater called the mind
叫做“心灵”的内在世界，
and only I can see what's in my mind and
只有我才能看到我内心的想法，
in this inner theata there's little pink
在这个内在世界里，有一些粉红色的小
elephants floating around.
象在漂浮。
So in other words, what's happened is my
换句话说，我的
perceptual systems gone wrong and I'm
感知系统出了问题，我正在
trying to indicate to you how it's gone
试图向你指出它是如何
wrong and what it's trying to tell me.
出错的，以及它想告诉我什么。
And the way I do that is by telling you
我的做法是告诉你，
real world for it to be telling the
现实世界中必须存在什么才能说
truth.
真话。
And so these little pink elephants,
所以这些粉红色的小象，
they're not in some inner theater. These
它们并不在某个内部剧场里。 这些粉
little pink elephants are hypothetical
红色的小象
things in the real world. And that's my
在现实世界中只是假设存在的事物。 这就是我向
way of telling you how my perceptual
你解释我的感知
systems telling me FIPS. So now let's do
系统如何告诉我 FIPS 的方式。 现在让我们
that with a chatbot. Yeah. because I
用聊天机器人来实现这个功能。 是的。 因为我
believe that current multimodal chatbots
认为目前的多模态聊天机器人
have subjective experiences and very few
具有主观体验，但很少
people believe that. But I'll try and
有人认同这一点。 但我会尽力
make you believe it. So suppose I have a
让你相信这一点。 假设我有一个
multimodal chatbot. It's got a robot arm
多模态聊天机器人。 它有一个机械臂，
so it can point and it's got a camera so
可以指向目标；它还有一个摄像头，
it can see things and I put an object in
可以观察物体。我把一个物体放在
front of it and I say point at the
它前面，然后说“指向这个
object. It goes like this. No problem.
物体”。 事情是这样的。 没问题。
Then I put a prism in front of its lens.
然后我在它的镜头前放了一个棱镜。
And so then I put an object in front of
然后我把一个物体放在
it and I say point at the object and it
它前面，我说指向那个物体，它就
goes there.
移动到那里。
And I say, "No, that's not where the
我说：“不，物体不在那里
object is. The object's actually
。物体实际上就在
straight in front of you, but I put a
你正前方，但我把一个
prism in front of your lens." And the
棱镜放在了你的镜头前面。”
chatbot says, "Oh, I see. The prism bent
聊天机器人说：“哦，我明白了。棱镜弯曲了
the light rays." So, um, the object's
光线。” 所以，嗯，物体
actually there, but I had the subjective
实际上就在那里，但我主观上
experience that it was there.
感觉它在那里。
Now, if the chatbot says that, is using
如果聊天机器人这样说，那么它使用“
the word subjective experience exactly
主观体验”这个词的方式就和
the way people use them. It's an
人们使用这个词的方式完全一样。 这是对正在发生的事情的
alternative view of what's going on.
另一种看法。
They're hypothetical states of the
它们是世界的一种假想状态
world. which if they were true would
。 如果这些说法属实，那就
mean my perceptual system wasn't lying.
意味着我的感知系统没有说谎。
And that's the best way I can tell you
这就是我能告诉你
what my perceptual system is doing when
我的感知系统在欺骗我时正在做什么的最好方式
it's lying to me. Now, we need to go
。 现在，我们需要
further to deal with sentience and
进一步探讨感知、
consciousness and feelings and emotions,
意识、感觉和情绪，
but I think in the end they're all going
但我认为最终它们都会
to be dealt with in a similar way.
以类似的方式得到处理。
There's no reason machines can't have
机器完全可以拥有
them all because people say machines
所有这些情感，尽管人们认为机器
can't have feelings. And people are
不能有情感。 人们
curiously confident about that. I have
对此表现出一种奇怪的自信。 我
no idea why. Suppose I make a battle
不知道为什么。 假设我制造了一个
robot and it's a little battle robot and
小型战斗机器人，
it sees a big battle robot that's much
它遇到了一个比它强大得多的大型战斗机器人
more powerful than it. It would be
。
really useful if it got scared.
如果它能感到害怕，那就太好了。
Now, when I get scared, um, various
现在，当我感到害怕时，嗯，会
physiological things happen that we
发生各种生理反应，我们
don't need to go into, and those won't
没必要深入探讨，而这些反应在
happen with the robot. But all the
机器人身上就不会发生。 但是所有
cognitive things like I better get the
认知上的事情，比如我最好赶紧
hell out of here and I better sort of
离开这里，我最好
change my way of thinking so I focus and
改变我的思维方式，这样我才能集中注意力，
focus and focus and don't get
不要
distracted. All of that will happen with
分心。 所有这些在机器人身上也会发生
robots, too. People will build in things
。 人们会建造一些东西，以便在遇到
they should get the hell out of there,
应该赶紧离开的情况时，
they get scared and run away. They'll
他们会感到害怕并逃跑。
have emotions then. They won't have the
那时他们就会有情绪了。 他们不会具备
physiological aspects, but they will
生理方面的能力，但会
have all the cognitive aspects. And I
具备所有认知方面的能力。 我
think it would be odd to say they're
认为说他们
just simulating emotions. No, they're
只是在模拟情感是很奇怪的。 不，他们
really having those emotions. The little
确实有这些情绪。 小
robot got scared and ran away. It's not
机器人吓坏了，跑开了。 它
running away because of adrenaline. It's
逃跑并不是因为肾上腺素飙升。 它之所以
running away because of a sequence of
逃跑，是因为
sort of neurological in its neural net
其神经网络过程中发生了一系列类似肾上腺素的神经过程，这些过程
processes happened which which have the
产生了
equivalent effect to adrenaline. So do
与肾上腺素类似的效果。 所以，做
you do you and it's not just adrenaline,
你自己就好，这不仅仅是肾上腺素的作用，
right? There's a lot of cognitive stuff
对吧？
goes on when you get scared. Yeah. So,
感到害怕时，大脑会发生很多认知上的变化。 是的。 那么，
do you think that
你认为
there is conscious AI? And when I say
存在有意识的人工智能吗？ 我所说的
conscious, I mean that represents the
有意识，是指它代表了
human has. There's two issues here.
人类所具有的意识的相同属性。 这里有两个问题。
There's a sort of empirical one and a
其中既有经验层面的，也有
philosophical one. I don't think there's
哲学层面的。 我认为
anything in principle that stops
原则上没有什么能阻止
machines from being conscious.
机器拥有意识。   在
that before we carry on. Suppose I take
我们继续之前，我先给你们做一个简单的演示。 假设我取下
your brain and I take one brain cell in
你的大脑，然后从你的大脑中取出一个脑细胞，
your brain and I replace it by this a
并用这个
bit black mirror-l like. I replace it by
有点像《黑镜》里的东西替换它。 我用
a little piece of nanotechnology that's
一小块纳米技术元件代替它，这块元件
just the same size that behaves in
大小相同，
exactly the same way when it gets pings
当它接收
from other neurons. It sends out pings
到其他神经元的信号时，它的行为方式也完全相同。 它
just as the brain cell would have. So
会像脑细胞一样发出信号。 所以
the other neurons don't know anything's
其他神经元并不知道发生了任何
changed.
变化。
Okay. I've just replaced one of your
好的。 我刚刚
brain cells with this little piece of
用这块
nanote technology. Would you still be
纳米技术替换了你脑中的一个细胞。 你还会保持
conscious?
意识清醒吗？   是的
Yeah. Now you can see where this
。 现在你应该明白这场
argument is going. Yeah. So if you
争论的走向了吧。 是的。 所以，如果你
replaced all of them as I replace them
像我一样把它们全部替换掉
all, at what point do you stop being
，那么你会在什么时候失去
conscious? Well, people think of
意识？ 人们通常认为
consciousness as this like ethereal
意识是一种虚无缥缈的
thing that exists maybe beyond the brain
东西，它可能存在于脑
cells. Yeah. Well, people have a lot of
细胞之外。 是的。 人们有很多
crazy ideas.
稀奇古怪的想法。
Um, people don't know what consciousness
嗯，人们不知道什么
is and they often don't know what they
是意识，他们通常也不知道意识的含义
mean by it. And then they fall back on
。 然后他们又会
saying, well, I know it cuz I've got it
说，嗯，我知道，因为我拥有它，
and I can see that I've got it and they
我能看到我拥有它，他们又会回到
fall back on this theata model of the
这种心智的theata模型，
mind which I think is nonsense. What do
我认为这是无稽之谈。
you think of consciousness as if you had
如果让你来定义意识，你会怎么看待
to try and define it? Is it because I
它？ 是因为我把它看作是
think of it as just like the awareness
对
of myself? I don't know. I think it's a
自我的认知吗？ 我不知道。 我认为
term we'll stop using. Suppose you want
我们应该停止使用这个词。 假设你想
to understand how a car works. Well, you
了解汽车的工作原理。 你
know, some cars have a lot of oomph and
知道，有些车动力很强劲，而
other cars have a lot less oomph. Like
有些车动力则比较弱。 就像
an Aston Martin's got lots of oomph. And
阿斯顿·马丁动力十足一样。 而
a little Toyota Corolla doesn't have
小型丰田卡罗拉动力并不
much oomph. But oomph isn't a very good
强劲。 但是，用“动力”
concept for understanding cars. Um, if
来理解汽车并不是一个好概念。 嗯，如果
you want to understand cars, you need to
你想了解汽车，你需要
understand about electric engines or
了解电动机或
petrol engines and how they work. And it
汽油发动机以及它们的工作原理。 它能
gives rise to oomph, but oomph isn't a
带来活力，但活力并不是一个
very useful explanatory concept. It's a
很有用的解释概念。 这是
kind of essence of a car. It's the
汽车的一种精髓。 它体现了
essence of an Aston Martin, but it
阿斯顿·马丁的精髓，但它并
doesn't explain much. I think
不能解释太多。 我认为
consciousness is like that. And I think
意识就是这样的。 我认为
we'll stop using that term, but I don't
我们会停止使用这个术语，但我
think there's anything any reason why a
认为没有任何理由阻止
machine shouldn't have it. If your view
机器拥有它。 如果你认为
of consciousness is that it
意识
intrinsically involves self-awareness,
本质上包含自我意识，
then the machine's got to have
那么机器就必须具有
self-awareness. He's got to have
自我意识。 他必须
cognition about its own cognition and
对自身的认知能力有认知
stuff. But
。 但
I'm a materialist through and through.
我彻头彻尾是个唯物主义者。
And I don't think there's any reason why
我认为机器没有任何理由
a machine shouldn't have consciousness.
不能拥有意识。
Do you think they do then have the same
你认为他们是否也像我们一样，
consciousness that we think of ourselves
认为自己是与生俱来的、
as being uniquely uh given as a gift
独一无二的礼物，并拥有同样的意识呢
when we're born? I'm ambivalent about
？ 我
that at present. So
目前对此态度比较矛盾。 所以
I don't think there's this hard line. I
我认为不存在这条硬性界限。 我
think as soon as you have a machine that
认为，一旦机器具备了
has some self-awareness,
一定的自我意识，
it's got some consciousness. Um, I think
它就具有了一定的意识。 嗯，我认为
it's an emergent property of a complex
这是复杂系统涌现出的特性
system. It's not a sort of essence
。 它并非一种
throughout the universe. It's you make
遍布宇宙的本质。 你构建了一个
this really complicated system that's
非常复杂的系统，
complicated enough to have a model of
复杂到足以建立自身的模型，
and it does perception. And I think then
并且它能够感知。 我认为，从那时起，
you're beginning to get a conscious
你就开始拥有有意识的
machines. So I don't think there's any
机器了。 所以我认为我们
now and conscious machines. I don't
现在拥有的和有意识的机器之间并没有明显的区别。 我不
think it's going to one day we're going
认为有一天我们会突然
to wake up and say, "Hey, if you put
醒悟，说：“嘿，如果你
this special chemical in, it becomes
注入这种特殊的化学物质，它就会有
conscious." It's not going to be like
意识。” 事情不会
that. I think we all wonder if these
那样。 我想我们都想知道，当我们不在电脑前时，这些
computers are like thinking like we are
电脑是否会像我们一样独立思考
on their own when we're not there. And
。
if they're experiencing emotions, if
如果他们正在经历情感，如果
they're contending with I think we
他们正在应对，我想我们
probably, you know, we think about
可能，你知道，我们会思考
things like love and things that are
诸如爱情之类的事情，以及一些
feel unique to biological species. Um,
感觉是生物物种独有的事情。 嗯，
are they sat there thinking? Are they do
他们是坐在那里思考吗？ 他们
they have concerns? I think they really
有顾虑吗？ 我认为他们确实在
are thinking and I think as soon as you
思考，而且我认为一旦你
make AI agents they will have concerns.
创造出人工智能代理，他们就会产生担忧。
If you wanted to make an effective AI
如果你想创建一个高效的人工智能
agent suppose you let's take a call
代理，假设你以呼叫
center. In a call center you have people
中心为例。 在呼叫中心，人们
at present they have all sorts of
现在有各种各样的
emotions and feelings which are kind of
情绪和感受，这在某种程度上是
useful. So suppose I call up the call
有用的。 假设我打电话给客服
center and I'm actually lonely and I
中心，其实我只是感到孤独，
don't actually want to know the answer
并不想知道
to why my computer isn't working. I just
我的电脑为什么不能正常工作。 我只是
want somebody to talk to. After a while,
想找个人聊聊天。 过一段时间，
the person in the call center will
呼叫中心的人
either get bored or get annoyed with me
要么会觉得无聊，要么会厌烦我，
and will terminate it.
然后就会挂断电话。
Well, you replace them by an AI agent.
嗯，你可以用人工智能代理来代替它们。
The AI agent needs to have the same kind
人工智能代理需要做出相同类型的
of responses. If someone's just called
反应。 如果有人
up because they just want to talk to the
打电话来只是想和
AI agent and we're happy to talk for the
人工智能客服聊天，而我们也乐意
whole day to the AI agent, that's not
和人工智能客服聊上一整天，这
good for business. And you want an AI
对业务来说并不好。 你想要的是一个人工智能
agent that either gets bored or gets
代理，它会感到无聊或
irritated and says, "I'm sorry, but I
恼火，然后说：“对不起，我
don't have time for this." And once it
没时间做这个。” 一旦它
does that, I think it's got emotions.
做到这一点，我认为它就有了情感。
Now, like I say, emotions have two
正如我所说，情感有两个
aspects to them. There's the cognitive
方面。 人类有认知
aspect and the behavioral aspect, and
方面、行为方面和生理方面
then there's a physiological aspect, and
，
those go together with us. And if the AI
这些方面与我们息息相关。 如果人工智能
agent gets embarrassed, it won't go red.
代理感到尴尬，它也不会变红。   是的
Yeah. Um, so there's no physiological
。 嗯，所以生理上的
skin won't start sweating. Yeah, but it
皮肤不会开始出汗。 是的，但它们
might have all the same behavior. And in
可能表现出完全相同的行为。 在
that case, I'd say yeah, it's having
这种情况下，我会说，是的，它有
emotion. It's got an emotion. So, it's
情感。 它蕴含着情感。 所以，它会有
going to have the same sort of cognitive
同样的认知
thought and then it's going to act upon
思维，然后
that cognitive in the same way, but
以同样的方式对这种认知思维采取行动，但
without the physiological responses. And
不会有生理反应。 脸
does that matter that it doesn't go red
不涨红又有什么关系呢
in the face? And it's just a different I
？ 这只是不同的，我的
mean, that's a response to the It makes
意思是，这是对……的回应，这使得
it somewhat different from us. Yeah. For
它与我们有些不同。 是的。
some things, the physiological aspects
有些事情，
are very important like love. They're a
比如爱情，生理因素非常重要。 他们离
long way from having love the same way
拥有和我们一样的爱情还很远
we do. But I don't see why they
。 但我看不出他们为什么
shouldn't have emotions. So I think
不能有情感。 所以我觉得
what's happened is people have a model
现在的问题是，人们对
of how the mind works and what feelings
大脑的运作方式、感觉
are and what emotions are and their
和情绪的理解存在一种
model is just wrong. What um what
错误的认知模型。 是什么
brought you to Google? You you worked at
让你想到谷歌呢？ 你在
Google for about a decade, right? Yeah.
谷歌工作了大约十年，对吧？ 是的。
What brought you there? I have a son who
是什么把你带到那里的？ 我有一个
has learning difficulties
有学习障碍的儿子，
and in order to be sure he would never
为了确保他永远不会
be out on the street, I needed to get
流落街头，我需要筹集
several million dollars and I wasn't
几百万美元，而
going to get that as an academic. I
作为一名学者，我是不可能筹集到这笔钱的。 我
tried. So, I taught a Corsera course in
试过。 所以，我开办了一门 Corsera 课程，
the hope that I'd make lots of money
希望以此赚很多钱
that way, but there was no money in
，但结果却一分钱也没赚到
that. Mhm. So I figured out well the
。 嗯。 所以我想，要想
only way to get millions of dollars is
赚到数百万美元，唯一的办法就是把
to sell myself to a big company.
自己卖给一家大公司。
And so when I was 65,
所以，在我 65 岁的时候，
fortunately for me, I had two brilliant
幸运的是，我有两位才华横溢的
students who produced something called
学生，他们开发出了
Alexet, which was neural net that was
Alexet，这是一个
very good at recognizing objects in
非常擅长识别图像中物体的神经网络
images. And
。
so Ilia and Alex and I set up a little
于是，伊利亚、亚历克斯和我成立了一家小
company and auctioned it. And we
公司，然后把它拍卖了。 我们
actually set up an auction where we had
实际上组织了一场拍卖，有
a number of big companies bidding for
很多大公司竞标
us.
。
And that company was called AlexNet. No,
那家公司名叫 AlexNet。 不，那个能够
the the the network that recognized
识别
objects was called Alexet. The company
物体的网络叫做 Alexet。 这家公司
was called DNN Research, deep neural
名为DNN Research，即深度神经
network research. And it was doing
网络研究公司。 它当时就做了
things like this. I'll put this graph up
类似这样的事情。 我会把这张图表显示
on the screen. That's that's Alexet.
在屏幕上。 那就是阿列克谢。
This picture shows eight images and Alex
这张图片展示了八张图片以及 Alex
Net's ability, which is your company's
Net 的能力，也就是贵公司
ability to spot what was in those
识别这些
images. Yeah. So, it could tell the
图片内容的能力。 是的。 所以，它可以
difference between various kinds of
区分各种
mushroom. And about 12% of imageet is
蘑菇。 其中约 12% 的图片是
dogs. And to be good at imageet, you
狗。 要想擅长图像识别，你
have to tell the difference between very
必须能够区分非常
similar kinds of dog. And it would got
相似的几种狗。 而且它必须
to be very good at that. And your your
非常擅长这一点。
company Alexet won several awards I
我相信，贵公司 Alexet 凭借其超越竞争对手的能力，赢得了多个奖项
outperform its competitors. And so
。 因此，
Google ultimately ended up acquiring
谷歌最终收购了
your technology. Google acquired that
你的技术。 谷歌收购了这项
technology and some other technology.
技术以及其他一些技术。
And you went to work at Google at age
你66岁的时候去谷歌工作，
what 66. I went at age 65 to work at
我65岁的时候去
Google. 65. And you left at age 76? 75.
谷歌工作。  65. 你76岁才离开？  75.
75. Okay. I worked there for more or
75. 好的。 我在那里工作了差不多整整
less exactly 10 years. And what were you
十年。 你当时在
doing there? Okay, they were very nice
那里做什么？ 好吧，他们
to me. They said they said pretty much
对我很友好。 他们说，基本上
you can do what you like. I worked on
你可以做任何你想做的事。 我曾参与过
something called distillation that did
一个叫做蒸馏的技术研究，它确实非常
really work well
有效，
and that's now used all the time in AI
现在
in AI and distillation is a way of
人工智能领域一直在使用蒸馏技术。蒸馏是一种将
taking what a big model knows a big
大型模型（大型
neural net knows and getting that
神经网络）所知道的
knowledge into a small neural net. Then
知识传递给小型神经网络的方法。
at the end I got very interested in
最后，我对模拟计算产生了浓厚的兴趣，
analog computation and whether it would
想知道是否有
be possible to get these big language
可能让这些大型语言
models running in analog hardware. So
模型在模拟硬件上运行。 所以
they used much less energy. And it was
他们使用的能源少得多。 正是在
when I was doing that work that I began
从事那项工作的过程中，我开始
to really realize how much better
真正意识到
digital is for sharing information.
数字化在信息共享方面有多么出色。   当时有
Was there a Eureka moment?
灵光乍现的时刻吗？   那段时间大概有
There was a Eureka month or two. Um and
一两个月的灵感迸发期。 嗯，
it was a sort of coupling of chat beauty
这有点像是聊天美容功能的
coming out although Google had very
推出，虽然谷歌
similar things a year earlier and I'd
一年前就推出了非常类似的功能，而且我
seen those and that had a big effect
看过那些功能，这
effect on me. The closest I had to a
对我产生了很大的影响。 我最接近
Eureka moment was when a Google system
灵光乍现的时刻，是谷歌的一个
called Palm was able to say why a joke
名为 Palm 的系统能够解释为什么一个笑话
was funny. And I'd always thought of
好笑。 我一直把它视为一个
that as a kind of landmark. If it can
里程碑。 如果它能
say why a joke's funny, it really does
说出一个笑话好笑的地方，那就说明它真的
understand and it could say why a joke
理解了，而且它能说出一个笑话
was funny.
好笑的原因。   再加上我
And that coupled with realizing why
意识到
digital is so much better than analog
数字技术在信息共享方面比模拟技术好得多，这让
suddenly made me very interested in AI
我突然对人工智能安全产生了浓厚的兴趣，
safety and that these things were going
并且意识到这些技术将会变得
to get a lot smarter than us. Why did
比我们聪明得多。
you leave Google? The main reason I left
你为什么离开谷歌？ 我离开
Google was cuz I was 75 and I wanted to
谷歌的主要原因是我已经75岁了，想
retire. I've done a very bad job of
退休。 我在这方面做得非常糟糕
that. The precise timing of when I left
。 我离开谷歌的确切时间
Google was so that I could talk freely
是为了能
at a conference at MIT, but I left
在麻省理工学院的会议上畅所欲言，但我离开的
because I was I'm old and I was finding
原因是，我年纪大了，发现
it harder to program. I was making many
编程越来越困难。 我在编程时犯了很多
more mistakes when I programmed, which
错误，这
is very annoying. You wanted to talk
很令人恼火。 你想
freely at a conference at MIT. Yes. At
在麻省理工学院的会议上畅所欲言。 是的。
MIT, organized by MIT Tech Review. What
由麻省理工学院科技评论组织，在麻省理工学院举办。
did you want to talk about freely? AI
你想畅所欲言地聊些什么？ 人工智能
safety. And you couldn't do that while
安全。
you were at Google. Well, I could have
你在谷歌的时候是做不到这一点的。 其实我
done it while I was at Google. And
在谷歌工作的时候就可以做了。
Google encouraged me to stay and work on
谷歌鼓励我留下来继续从事
AI safety and said I could do whatever I
人工智能安全方面的工作，并说我可以
liked on AI safety. You kind of sense to
在人工智能安全领域做任何我想做的事情。
yourself if you work for a big company.
如果你在大公司工作，你就会慢慢意识到这一点。
You don't feel right saying things that
你觉得说些
will damage the big company. Even if you
会损害大公司利益的话不太合适。 即使你
could get away with it, it just feels
能逃脱惩罚，
wrong to me. I didn't leave because I
我还是觉得这样做不对。 我离开并不是因为我
was cross with anything Google was
对谷歌的任何
doing. I think Google actually behaved
做法感到不满。 我认为谷歌实际上表现得
very responsibly. When they had these
非常负责任。 当他们拥有这些
big chat bots, they didn't release them
大型聊天机器人时，他们
possibly because they were worried about
可能因为担心损害
their reputation. they had a very good
自身声誉而没有发布。 他们
reputation and they didn't want to
声誉很好，不想
damage it. So open AI didn't have a
损害自己的声誉。 所以 OpenAI 当时还没有
reputation and so they could afford to
名声，因此他们有能力
take the gamble. I mean there's also a
承担这种风险。 我的意思是，现在也有
big conversation happening around how it
很多人在讨论这
will cannibalize their core business in
将如何蚕食他们在搜索领域的核心业务
search. There is now. Yes. Yeah. Yeah.
。 现在已经有了。 是的。 是的。 是的。
some degree I guess that contending with
我想，这在某种程度上也是老一辈创新者面临的困境，那就是如何应对
bad skin. I've had it and I'm sure many
糟糕的皮肤状况。 我已经受够了，我相信很多
of you listening have had it too or
听众也受够了，或者
maybe you have it right now. I know how
你们现在可能正经历着这种痛苦。 我知道
draining it can be, especially if you're
这会让人很疲惫，特别是如果你
like I am. So, let me tell you about
像我一样，从事需要经常做演讲的工作。 那么，让我来告诉你们
something that's helped both my partner
一种对
and me and my sister, which is red light
我和我的伴侣以及我的妹妹都很有帮助的方法，那就是红光
therapy. I only got into this a couple
疗法。 我几年前才开始接触这个领域
of years ago, but I wish I'd known a
，但我希望我能早点知道
little bit sooner. I've been using our
。 我使用我们
show sponsors Boncharg's infrared sauna
节目赞助商 Boncharg 的红外线桑拿
blanket for a while now, but I just got
毯已经有一段时间了，但我最近也
hold of their red light therapy mask as
入手了他们的红光治疗面罩
well. Red light has been proven to have
。 红光已被证实
so many benefits for the body. Like any
对身体有很多益处。 就像
area of your skin that's exposed will
你身体任何暴露在外的皮肤区域一样，
see a reduction in scarring, wrinkles,
疤痕、皱纹
and even blemishes. It also helps with
甚至瑕疵都会减少。 它还有助于改善
complexion. It boosts collagen, and it
肤色。 它能促进胶原蛋白生成，其作用机制是
does that by targeting the upper layers
通过作用于
of your skin. And Boncharge ships
皮肤表层。  Boncharge 提供
worldwide with easy returns and a
全球配送服务，退货方便快捷，
year-long warranty on all of their
所有产品均享有一年保修
products. So, if you'd like to try it
。 所以，如果您想亲自尝试一下
yourself, head over to
，请访问
bondcharge.com/diary
bondcharge.com/diary
and use code diary for 25% off any
并使用代码 diary，即可享受全场任何产品 25% 的折扣
product sitewide. Just make sure you
。 请务必
order through this link.
通过此链接下单。
bondcharge.com/diary
bondcharge.com/diary，
with code diary. Make sure you keep what
代码为 diary。 请务必将
I'm about to say to yourself. I'm
我接下来要说的话保密。 我
inviting 10,000 of you to come even
邀请你们中的 10,000 人更
deeper into the diary of a CEO. Welcome
深入地了解一位 CEO 的日记。 欢迎
to my inner circle. This is a brand new
来到我的核心圈子。 这是
private community that I'm launching to
我即将向全世界推出的一个全新的私人社区
the world. We have so many incredible
。 我们这里发生了很多不可思议的
things that happen that you are never
事情，但你却从未
shown. We have the briefs that are on my
见过。
iPad when I'm recording the
我在录制对话时，iPad 上会显示一些简要说明
conversation. We have clips we've never
。 我们有一些从未
released. We have behindthe-scenes
公开过的视频片段。 我们会
conversations with the guests. and also
与嘉宾进行幕后交流。 还有
the episodes that we've never ever
我们从未
released and so much more. In the
发布过的剧集等等。 在这个
circle, you'll have direct access to me.
圈子里，你可以直接联系到我。
You can tell us what you want this show
您可以告诉我们您希望这个节目
to be, who you want us to interview, and
成为什么样子，您希望我们采访谁，以及
the types of conversations you would
您
love us to have. But remember, for now,
希望我们进行哪些类型的对话。 但请记住，目前
we're only inviting the first 10,000
我们只邀请前 10,000 名
people that join before it closes. So,
加入的人，活动即止。 所以，
if you want to join our private closed
如果您想加入我们的私人封闭
community, head to the link in the
社区，请点击
description below or go to
下方说明中的链接或访问
daccircle.com.
daccircle.com。
I will speak to you there.
我会在那里和你谈谈。
I'm continually shocked by the types of
我总是对那些会
individuals that listen to this
听我们
conversation um because they come up to
谈话的人感到震惊，因为他们
me sometimes. So I hear from
有时会走过来和我说话。 所以我听取了
politicians, I hear from some real
政界人士、普通
people, I hear from entrepreneurs all
民众以及
over the world, whether they are the
世界各地企业家的意见，无论他们是正在
entrepreneurs building some of the
打造
biggest companies in the world or their,
世界顶级公司的企业家，还是处于
you know, early stage startups. For
早期创业阶段的企业家。 对于
those people that are listening to this
那些正在收听这段
conversation now that are in positions
对话的、身居要职
of power and influence,
、拥有影响力的人士，比如
world leaders, let's say, what's your
世界领导人，你们想
message to them?
对他们说些什么？
I'd say what you need is highly
我认为你们需要的是高度
regulated capitalism. That's what seems
监管的资本主义。 这似乎是
to work best. And what would you say to
最有效的方法。 那么，你会对那些不在相关
not doesn't work in the industry,
行业工作、
somewhat concerned about the future,
对未来感到有些担忧、
doesn't know if they're helpless or not.
不知道自己是否无能为力的普通人说些什么呢？
What should they be doing in their own
他们应该在自己的生活中做些什么
lives?
？
My feeling is there's not much they can
我的感觉是他们能做的并不多
do. This isn't isn't going to be decided
。 这件事不会
by just as climate change isn't going to
由人们将塑料袋与可堆肥垃圾分开来决定，就像气候变化不会
be decided by people separating out the
由人们将塑料袋与可堆肥垃圾分开来决定一样
plastic bags from the um compostables.
。
That's not going to have much effect.
那不会产生多大影响。   最终结果将
It's going to be decided by whether the
取决于能否
can be kept under control. I don't think
控制住大型能源公司的游说者。 我认为
there's much people can do to except for
除了向
try and pressure their governments to
政府施压，迫使
force the big companies to work on AI
大公司在人工智能
safety that they can do.
安全方面做出他们力所能及的努力之外，人们能做的并不多。
You've lived a a fascinating fascinating
你的
winding life. I think one of the things
人生精彩纷呈，跌宕起伏。 我认为
most people don't know about you is that
大多数人不知道的一点是，
your family has a
你的家族有着
big history of being involved in
参与众多重大事件的辉煌历史
tremendous things. You have a family
。 你的家谱
tree which is one of the most impressive
是
that I've ever seen or read about. Your
我见过或读过的最令人印象深刻的家谱之一。 你的
great greatgrandfather George Bull
曾祖父乔治·布尔
founded the Boolean algebra logic which
创立了布尔代数逻辑，这
is one of the foundational principles of
是现代计算机科学的基础原理之一
modern computer science. You have uh
。 你的曾
your great great grandmother Mary
曾祖母玛丽·
Everest Bull who was a mathematician and
埃弗勒斯·布尔是一位数学家和
educator who made huge leaps forward in
教育家，据我所知，她在数学领域取得了巨大的进步
ascertain. Um I mean I can the list goes
。 嗯，我的意思是，我可以列举很多很多
on and on and on. I mean, your great
。 我的意思是，
great uncle George Everest is what Mount
珠穆朗玛峰就是以你的曾祖叔乔治·埃弗勒斯的名字
Everest is named after.
命名的。
Is that is that correct? I think he's my
是这样吗？ 我认为他是我的曾曾祖
great great great uncle. His his niece
叔。 他的侄女
married George Bull.
嫁给了乔治·布尔。
So Mary Mary Bull was Mary Everest Bull.
所以玛丽·玛丽·布尔就是玛丽·埃弗勒斯·布尔。
Um she was the niece of Everest. And
嗯，她是埃弗勒斯的侄女。
your first cousin once removed, Joan
你的表妹琼·
Hinton, was involved in the a nuclear
欣顿（Joan Hinton）是一位核
physicist who worked on the Manhattan
物理学家，曾参与曼哈顿
project, which is the World War II
计划，该计划是二战期间
development of the first nuclear bomb.
研制第一颗原子弹的项目。   是的
Yeah. She was one of the two female
。 她是
physicists at Los Alamos.
洛斯阿拉莫斯国家实验室仅有的两名女物理学家之一。
And then after they dropped the bomb,
之后，在他们投下那颗炸弹之后，
she moved to China. Why? She was very
她搬到了中国。 为什么？ 她
cross with them dropping the bomb. And
对他们投放炸弹的行为非常生气。
her family had a lot of links with
她的家族与中国有着密切的联系
China. Her mother was friends with
。 她母亲和莫主席是朋友。
Quite weird.
真奇怪。
Jeffrey,
杰弗里，当你回顾自己的人生时，
we have the hindsight you have now and
我们拥有你现在的后见之明和
the ret retrospective clarity,
清晰的回顾视角，
what might you have done differently if
如果
you were advising me?
你当时给我提建议，你会采取哪些不同的做法？
I guess I have two pieces of advice. One
我想给两点建议。 第一，
is if you have an intuition that people
如果你直觉认为人们
are doing things wrong and there's a
做事的方式是错误的，并且有
better way to do things, don't give up
更好的做事方法，不要
on that intuition just because people
因为人们
say it's silly. Don't give up on the
说这种直觉很愚蠢就放弃它。 在
intuition until you figured out why it's
弄清楚直觉错在哪里之前，不要放弃你的直觉
wrong. Figured out for yourself why that
。 自己弄明白为什么这种
intuition isn't correct. And usually
直觉是错误的。
it's wrong if it disagrees with
如果它与其他人的观点不一致，通常就是错误的，
everybody else and you'll eventually
你最终会
figure out why it's wrong.
明白它错在哪里。
But just occasionally you'll have an
但偶尔你会有一种
intuition that's actually right and
直觉，它竟然是正确的，而
everybody else is wrong. And I lucked
其他人都是错的。 我真是走运了
out that way. Early on I thought neural
。 早期我就认为神经
nets are definitely the way to go to
网络绝对是实现
make AI and almost everybody said that
人工智能的正确途径，几乎所有人都说这
was crazy and I stuck with it because I
是疯了，但我坚持了下来，因为我
couldn't. It seemed to me it was
不能放弃。 在我看来，这
obviously right.
显然是正确的。
your intuitions isn't going to work if
如果
you have bad intuitions. But if you have
你直觉不好，那么“你应该坚持自己的直觉”这种想法就行不通了。 但是，如果你
bad intuitions, you're never going to do
直觉不好，
anything anyway, so you might as well
反正你什么也做不成，所以你还不如坚持自己的直觉
stick with them.
。
And in your own career journey, is there
在你的职业生涯中，有没有哪
anything you look back on and say, "With
件事让你回首往事时会想：“以
the hindsight I have now, I should have
我现在的眼光来看，当时我应该
taken a different approach at that
采取不同的方法
juncture."
。”
I wish I'd spent more time with my wife
我希望我能多花些时间陪伴我的妻子
and with my children when they were
和孩子们，尤其是在他们还
little.
小的时候。
I was kind of obsessed with work.
我当时有点痴迷于工作。
Your wife passed away. Yeah. From
你的妻子去世了。 是的。
ovarian cancer. No. Or that was another
卵巢癌。 不，或者那是她的另一个
wife. Okay. Um I had two wives to have
妻子。 好的。 嗯，我有两个妻子都得了
cancer. Oh, really? Sorry. The first one
癌症。 哦真的吗？ 对不起。 第一名
died of ovarian cancer and the second
死于卵巢癌，第二名
one died of pancreatic cancer. And you
死于胰腺癌。 你是不是很后悔没
wish you'd spent more time with her?
多花点时间陪她？
With the second wife? Yeah. Who was a
和第二任妻子？ 是的。 谁是位
wonderful person?
很棒的人？   你
Why did you say that in your 70s? What
七十多岁了，为什么会说出这样的话？
is it that you've you figured out that I
你已经发现了什么我
might not know yet?
还不知道的事情？
Oh, just cuz she's gone and I can't
哦，就因为她走了，我
spend more time with her now. Mhm.
现在不能再和她待在一起了。 嗯。
But you didn't know that at the time.
但你当时并不知道这一点。
At the time, you think
当时，你以为
I mean it was likely I would die before
我的意思是，
her just cuz she was a woman and I was a
仅仅因为她是女人而我是
man. Um I didn't
男人，我就很可能比她先死吗？ 嗯，我没有，
I just didn't spend enough time when I
我只是没能在有时间的时候花足够的时间
could.
。
I I think I I inquire there because I
我觉得我之所以在那里提问，是因为我
think there's many of us that are so
认为我们很多人都太
consumed with what we're doing
专注于自己的
professionally that we kind of assume
职业，以至于我们有点想当然地认为我们的
immortality with our partners because
伴侣会永远陪伴在我们身边，因为
they've always been there. So we Yeah. I
他们一直都在那里。 是的。 我的
mean she was very supportive of me
意思是，她非常支持我
spending a lot of time working but and
花很多时间工作，但是，
why did you say your children as well?
你为什么也提到你的孩子呢？
What's the what's the Well, I didn't
嗯，我小时候没花
spend enough time with them when they
足够的时间陪伴他们，
and you regret that now. Yeah.
现在我很后悔。 是的。
If you um if you had a closing message
如果你要对
for for my for my listeners about AI and
我的听众们说一些关于人工智能和
AI safety, what would that be? Jeffrey,
人工智能安全方面的结束语，你会说什么？ 杰弗里，
there's still a chance that we can
我们仍然有机会
figure out how to develop AI that won't
找到开发人工智能的方法，让它不会
want to take over from us. And because
想要取代我们。 正因为存在这种
there's a chance, we should put enormous
可能性，我们才应该投入大量
resources into trying to figure that out
资源去弄清楚这一点，
because if we don't, it's going to take
否则它就会
over. And are you hopeful?
控制我们。 你抱有希望吗？
I just don't know. I'm agnostic.
我真的不知道。 我是不可知论者。
you must get get bed get in bed at night
你晚上必须上床睡觉，
and when you're thinking to yourself
当你思考各种
about probabilities of outcomes there
结果的概率时，肯定会有
must be a bias in one direction because
一种倾向，因为
there certainly is for me I imagine
对我来说肯定有。我想
everyone listening now has a
现在每个听众心里都有一个
internal prediction that they might not
预测，他们可能不会
say out loud but of how they think it's
说出口，但就是他们认为事情会如何发展。
going to play out I really don't know I
我真的不知道，真的
genuinely don't know I think it's
不知道。我觉得这
incredibly uncertain when I'm feeling
非常不确定。当我
slightly depressed I think people are
有点沮丧的时候，我觉得“人们都
toast is going to take over while I'm
完蛋了”这种想法会占据上风；而当我心情愉快的时候，这种想法又会占据上风
feeling cheerful. I think we'll figure
。 我想我们总能
out a way. Maybe one of the facets of
找到办法。 或许作为人类的一个方面
being a human um is because we've always
是，因为我们一直都在
been here, like we were saying about our
这里，就像我们刚才谈到我们所
loved ones and our relationships, we
爱的人和我们的关系时一样，我们
assume casually that we will always be
理所当然地认为我们会一直在
here and we'll always figure everything
这里，我们会一直解决所有问题
out. But there's a beginning and an end
。 但万物皆有始有终，
to everything as we saw from the
就像
dinosaurs. I mean, yeah. And
恐龙的灭绝一样。 我的意思是，是的。
we have to face the possibility
我们必须面对这样的可能性：
that unless we do something soon,
如果我们不尽快采取行动，
we're near the end.
我们就接近末日了。
We have a closing tradition on this
本播客有个结尾的传统，
podcast where the last guest leaves a
最后一位嘉宾会
question in their diary. And the
在日记里留下一个问题。
question that they've left for you is
他们留给你们的问题是：在
with everything that you see ahead of
你们所看到的未来
us,
，
what is the biggest threat you see to
你们认为对人类幸福的最大威胁是什么
human happiness?
？
I think the joblessness is a fairly
我认为失业是人类幸福面临的一个相当
urgent short-term threat to human
紧迫的短期威胁
happiness. I think if you make lots and
。 我认为，如果让很多
lots of people unemployed, even if they
人失业，即使他们
get universal basic income, um they're
获得全民基本收入，他们也
not going to be happy
不会快乐，
because they need purpose. Because they
因为他们需要目标感。 因为他们
need purpose. Yes. And struggle. They
需要目标。 是的。 并努力奋斗。 他们
need to feel they're contributing
需要觉得自己
something. They're useful. And do you
有所贡献。 它们很有用。 你
think that outcome that there's going to
认为
be huge job displacement is more
出现大规模就业岗位流失的
probable than not? Yes, I do. And what
可能性有多大？ 是的，我愿意。 而
sort of that one I think is definitely
我认为，这种可能性绝对
more probable than not. If I worked in a
大于不可能的可能性。 如果我在
call center, I'd be terrified.
呼叫中心工作，我会非常害怕。
And what's the time frame for that in
那么，
terms of mass jobs? I think it's
大规模就业岗位的实现需要多长时间？ 我认为这种情况已经
beginning to happen already. I read an
开始出现了。 我
article in the Atlantic recently that
最近在《大西洋月刊》上读到一篇文章，文章
said it's already getting hard for
说
university graduates to get jobs. And
大学毕业生找工作已经越来越难了。
part of that may be that people are
部分原因可能是人们
already using AI for the jobs they would
已经在利用人工智能来从事他们原本可以从事的工作
have got. I spoke to the CEO of a major
。 我与一家人尽皆知、广为人知的大公司的首席执行官交谈过，
of people use, and he said to me in DMs
他在私信中告诉我，
that they used to have seven just over
他们过去有
7,000 employees. He said uh by last year
七千多名员工。 他说，呃，到去年，
they were down to I think 5,000. He said
他们的人数好像已经降到了 5000 人。 他说
right now they have 3,600. And he said
他们现在有3600人。 他还说，
by the end of summer because of AI
到夏季结束时，由于人工智能
agents they'll be down to 3,000. So
代理的出现，他们的人数将减少到 3000 人。 所以，
you've got So it's happening already.
它已经发生了。   是的
Yes. He's halfed his workforce because
。 他已经裁减了一半的员工，因为
AI agents can now handle 80% of the
人工智能代理现在可以处理 80% 的
customer service inquiries and other
客户服务咨询和其他
things. So it's it's happening already.
事务。 所以，这件事已经发生了。   是的
Yeah. So urgent action is needed. Yep. I
。 因此，必须采取紧急行动。 是的。 我
don't know what that urgent action is.
不知道那项紧急行动是什么。
That's a tricky one because that depends
这很难说，因为这
very much on the political system and
很大程度上取决于政治制度，而
wrong direction at present. I mean what
目前所有的政治制度都在朝着错误的方向发展。 我的意思是，
do we need to do? Save up money? Like do
我们该怎么办？ 攒钱？ 比如
we save money? Do we move to another
我们能省钱吗？ 我们搬到
part of the world? I don't know. What
世界其他地方去吗？ 我不知道。
would you tell your kids to do? They
你会告诉你的孩子该怎么做？ 他们
said, "Dad, like there's going to be
说：“爸爸，好像会有
loads of job displacement." Because I
很多人失业似的。” 因为我曾在
worked for Google for 10 years. is they
谷歌工作了10年。 他们
have enough money. Okay. Okay. [__] So,
有足够的钱吗？ 好的。 好的。 他妈的。 所以，
they're not typical. What if they didn't
他们并不典型。 如果他们
have money? Trained to be a plumber.
没钱怎么办？ 接受过水管工培训。
Really? Yeah.
真的吗？ 是的。
Jeffrey, thank you so much. You're the
杰弗里，非常感谢你。 我想，你是
first Nobel Prize winner that I've ever
我这辈子遇到的第一位诺贝尔奖得主，我们进行了
had a conversation with, I think, in my
交谈
life. So, that's a tremendous honor. And
。 所以，这是莫大的荣幸。
you you you received that award for a
您获得该奖项是对您
lifetime of exceptional work and pushing
一生杰出工作和推动
the world forward in so many profound
世界进步的诸多深刻贡献的肯定，这些贡献
ways that will lead to great and that
将带来巨大的进步，并且已经带来了对
things that matter so much to us. And
我们来说非常重要的进步。
now you've turned this season in your
现在，你把人生中的这个阶段用来
life to shining a light on some of your
展示你
own work, but also on the the the
自己的一些作品，同时也关注
broader risks of AI and how um and how
人工智能更广泛的风险，以及
it might impact us adversely. And
它可能对我们产生的不利影响。
there's very few people that have worked
很少有人曾在
inside the machine of a Google or a big
谷歌或大型
tech company that have contributed to
科技公司内部工作，为
the field of AI that are now at the very
人工智能领域做出过贡献，如今却站在最
forefront of warning us against the very
前沿，警告我们警惕他们曾经参与
thing that they worked upon. There are
研发的东西。
actually surprising number of us now.
实际上，我们现在的人数相当多。
They're not as uh as public and they're
他们不像公众人物那样活跃，而且
actually quite hard to get to have these
实际上很难与他们进行这类
kinds of conversations because many of
对话，因为
them are still in that industry. So, you
他们中的许多人仍然身处那个行业。 所以，你
know, someone who tries to contact these
知道，如果有人经常尝试联系这些
people often and ask invites them to
人，并邀请他们
have conversations, they often are a
进行对话，他们通常会有些
little bit hesitant to speak openly.
犹豫，不愿坦诚交流。
They speak privately, but they're less
他们私下里会谈论这件事，但不太
willing to openly because maybe maybe
愿意公开谈论，因为或许
they still have something at some sort
他们仍然受到某种
of incentives at play. I have an
利益的驱使。 我
advantage over them, which is I'm older,
比他们有优势，那就是我年纪大，
so I'm unemployed, so I can say what I
失业，所以我可以畅所欲言。
Well, there you go. So, thank you for
好吧，就是这样。 所以，谢谢你所做的一切
doing what you do. It's a real honor and
。 这是我莫大的荣幸，
please do continue to do it. Thank you.
请继续这样做。 谢谢。
Thank you so much.
太感谢了。
think I'm joking when I say that, but
我说这话的时候，人们以为我在开玩笑，但
I'm not. The plumbing fish. Yeah. Yeah.
我不是。 水管鱼。 是的。 是的。
And plumbers are pretty well paid.
而且水管工的收入相当不错。
[Music]
[音乐]